I want to be a jockey when I grow up, ya I want to be a jockey when I grow up
当我长大后我想成为一个骑士，你 当我长大后我想成为一个骑师
I'm down for Heathfield and
我对希思菲尔德和
South of Amena...
南阿美…
we are going to Africa
我们要去非洲
and trying to teach people
并试图教人
I don't think you want to go to university
我不相信你 想上大学
if you want to be an astronaut
如果你想成为一名宇航员
I'd like to
我想去
find out all about the moon and all that
找出所有 月亮和所有
Is it important to fight? yes!
它是重要的战斗？是的！
I want to be a jockey when I grow up, ya I want to be a jockey when I grow up
当我长大后我想成为一个骑士，你 当我长大后我想成为一个骑师
Tony was already an apprentice at Tommy Gosling's Racing Stables in Epsom
托尼已经是一个学徒 汤米小鹅的赛车马厩泻
when he left school at fifteen.
当他十五岁离开学校。
this is a photo finish of
这是一个完成的照片
when I rode at Newbury
当我骑在纽伯里
I'm the one with the white cap
我是一个白色的帽子
I was beaten a length and a half for third
我打了一个长度 一个半第三
and I had a photo finish
我有一个终点
so I took it out the box and kept it as a souvenir
所以我把它从盒子里拿出来 把它作为纪念品
What would you do if you don't make it as a jockey?
如果你不怎么 把它作为一个赛马吗？
I don't know
我不知道
if I knew I couldn't be one I'd get out of the game
如果我知道，我不能一 我滚出去的游戏
I wouldn't bother
我不会打扰
What do you think you would do then?
你认为你会怎么办？
learn taxis
学习出租车
Tony didn't make it as a jockey.
托尼没有把它作为一个骑师。
He had three races, wasn't placed and gave it up.
他有三场比赛，不放 而放弃了。
At 21 he was 'doing the knowledge'
21岁的他是做学问”
learning to be a London cabbie
学习是一个伦敦出租车司机
I will be a cab driver and I know I will
我将是一个出租车司机 我知道我会
and I'm going to prove every person who think I can't be a cab driver wrong
我要证明每个人 他们认为我不能一个出租车司机的错
and I'm going to get that badge and put it right in their face
我要把这 徽章放在他们的脸上的权利
just to tell them how wrong they can be
只是告诉他们怎样 他们可以是错误的
and how under estimated I am
如何在估计我
it's surprising who you pick-up, you see..
令人惊讶的是你拾取， 你看..
I once met Kojak, I picked him up
我曾经见过克捷，我把它捡起来
and Warren Mitchell or Alf Garnett, you know...
沃伦和米切尔或 阿尔夫-加内特，你知道的…
and I said "oh Hello Warren, how are you mate? good to see ya."
我说：“哦，你好，沃伦，如何 你的伴侣？很高兴见到你。”
so he ends up saying "I want to go to Langan's Brasserie
所以他说：“我想去 在兰甘的餐馆
you know Stratton Street, Langan's"
你知道斯特拉顿街， 阑干”
so half way there I said listen, I said  "Warren, it wouldn't...
所以有一半的我说你听， 我说：“沃伦，那就错了。
I said "It wouldn't be you if you don't sort of..
我说，“它不会是你 如果你不点..
come out with Alf you know, I mean.. give us a..
出来，你知道阿尔夫， 我的意思是..给我们。
let's see how he's going you know"
让我们看看他要你知道”
so straight away he's brought Alf Garnett to life
直掉他 阿尔夫-加内特的生活了
in the back of me cab
在我的车厢
so
所以
we are on the way to Langan's and all I can hear is Alf Garnett
我们对龙眼的方式和所有 我可以听到的是阿尔夫-加内特
"you know... it's the labour government"
你知道的。这是工党政府”
when we get there
当我们到达那里的时候
I said "thanks Warren, terrific mate.
我说：“谢谢 沃伦，了不起的队友。
so he gave me exactly
所以他给了我完全
listen, I said "I know you're Alf Garnett and you're having trouble.."
听着，我说：“我知道你 阿尔夫-加内特和你有麻烦了。”
I said "but I want you to become Warren Mitchell now..
我说，“但我希望你成为 沃伦米切尔现在。
my tip is 20 odd pence or whatever..."
我的建议是20 奇便士或任何……”
he said "son..."
他说：“儿子……”
as Alf Garnett still
作为阿尔夫-加内特依然
"you know Alf's doing bad at the moment I can't afford it"
“你知道阿尔夫做不好 此刻我负担不起”
and he walked away and like...
他走了，就像…
he done me like a kipper
他做了我喜欢腌鱼
What does it take to be a good cabbie?
它带什么 是一个好司机吗？
I think myself, a happy-go-lucky character
我认为我自己，一个 随遇而安的性格
and
和
take as much as what any other person couldn't take in a normal job because
采取什么其他人一样 不能在一个正常的工作，因为
it's a big world out there and everyone is a different character that I pick up
这是一个大的世界，每个人都 是一个不同的角色，我拿起
there attitudes... some of them like the city gents, the typical
我们的态度…他们中的一些人 喜欢城市绅士，典型的
"Waterloo, driver please, in five minutes"
“滑铁卢，驱动程序 请在五分钟”，
I sort of say "Hold on mate I'll get my helicopter out of the boot."
我这样说“我会坚持的伴侣 直升机的引导。”
I love being a taxi driver I like the outdoor life
我喜欢做一个出租车司机 我喜欢户外生活
the independance, there's no one to govern me or say
该independance，没有人 治理我或者说
"you've got to be in at a certain time."
“你必须 在一定的时间。”
sometimes on Saturday mornings I go to the pictures
有时在星期六的早上 我去看电影
sometimes with my friends and sometimes with him
有时我的朋友 有时他
you don't! -I do!
你不！ 我愿意。
she don't
她不
I don't ever see ya!
我从来没有看到你！
you go to different pictures
你去不同的图片
Have you got a girlfriend? -no
你有女朋友吗？ -不
Would you like to have a girlfriend?
你想有一个女朋友吗？
no
没有
do you understand 'the four F's?'
你知道四个F？”
find them, feed them and forget them
找到他们，给他们 忘记他们
for the other F I'll let you use your own discrimination
对于其他的我会让你 用你自己的歧视
I mean...
我的意思是…
this one
这一个
I tried the three F's
我试了三个F
but I couldn't forget her
但我不能忘记她
I used to work in a pub
我曾经在一家酒吧工作
just on Friday nights
就在星期五的晚上
barmaids... barmaiding...
酒吧女招待…barmaiding…
and then
然后
and then from there one night I went to a discotheque
然后有一天晚上 我去迪斯科舞厅
he was in the pub earlier on
他在酒吧前面
afterwards we went to a discotheque and Tony was standing there
后来我们去迪斯科舞厅 和托尼正站在那里
and I just... from there I just...
我只是… 从那里，我只是…
that was it
这是它
I couldn't get rid of him
我无法摆脱他
And why did you fall in love with him?
为什么你跌倒 爱上他？
I don't know
我不知道
I don't know how you've put up with me for so long
我不知道你 忍受我这么久
sometimes I don't know how I stand him
有时我不知道 我受不了他
but what is it that  you love about... - I like his personality
但是，什么是你喜欢的… 我爱他的个性
it doesn't matter who it is he don't change for nobody
是谁并不重要 他不要为没有人
there's only one ambition really I want a baby son
只有一个野心，真的 我想要一个儿子
if I see my baby son that is my ambition fulfilled
如果我看到我的宝贝儿子 那是我的目标实现
no one know that only you now
没有人知道 现在只有你
we've got two children Nicky's six and a half
我们有两个孩子 妮基六岁半
Jodi's two and a half nearly three
朱迪的两个半 近三
and I'm having another one in March
我又有了另一个 在3月
Who looks after them? Or, do you share it up?
谁来照顾他们？ 或者，你分享一下吗？
me basically, yeah
我基本上，是的
he does take them out quite a lot
他带他们出去 相当多
but
但
telling offs and smacks is all left to me
告诉被打 都是留给我的
I have to do all of that
我做了这一切
he don't like smacking them
他不想揍他们
he don't like telling them off
他不喜欢告诉他们了
unless it's really.. really.. - anything serious then I would
除非这是真的。真的。 -严重的话我会
there you are... see that baby one?
你… 看到宝宝吗？
So what advantages do you think you've had over
这样的优点是什么 你认为你有
some of the other people we've filmed?
其他一些人我们拍摄的？
well.. academically, probably they've had more advantages over me
好的。在学术上，可能他们 在我的优势
either by the fact they've had prep schools from a very early age
通过他们的事实 预备学校从很早的年龄
they've benefited by it which, you know, it tells obviously in this film
他们的受益者，你知道的， 它告诉显然在这片
but as far as, you know, the stability and the backgrounds with their parents
但是，你知道，稳定性 与他们的父母的背景
they've missed out on that
他们已经错过了，
Ton.. I don't like them near me
吨。我不喜欢他们靠近我
- come on - have a piece of bread each
-来吧 有一片面包每个
here Jodi..
这里Jodi ..
Jodi..
Jodi ..
being in a prep school they're missing the love and the care of what every
在预科学校他们失踪了 爱和照顾每一个
Eastender always gets
eastender总是
you know, gives their children each time they come home from work
你知道，给自己的孩子 每一次他们下班回家
and the parents, you know
和父母，你知道的
sometimes obviously are not going to be there cause they are away at prep school
有时，显然不会 这导致他们走在预备学校
they're missing
他们失踪了
the love and affection you know, what they are craving for
爱和感情 你知道，他们所渴望的
when my kids are growing up, I want to see the change in them, all the time
我的孩子们长大的时候，我想 看到他们的变化，所有的时间
so I have my own memories of when they was a kid and how they were
所以我有我自己的回忆，当他们 还是个孩子的时候，他们是如何
you know and what they were like
你知道的 他们都喜欢
would everybody please sit round now and get on with their work?
会请大家围坐在我们的 做他们的工作？
I don't want to see any backs to me
我不想看到任何背我
there shouldn't be anyone turning around Tony, do you hear as well?
不应该有任何的回头 托尼，你听到了吗？
get on with you're work in front
GE  t在你工作前
Tony!
托尼！
don't turn around again!
不回来！
education is just a thing to say "my son is higher than him"
教育是一件事要说 “我的儿子比他高”
or "my son had a better background than him"
“我的儿子有一个更好的 背景比他”
I mean
我的意思是
I'm as good or even better than most of them people
我为好或更好 比他们中的大多数人
especially on this program
尤其是在这个程序
I mean
我的意思是
I'm one of the tailenders you'll think oh the Eastend boy
我是你认为的尾页 哦，伦敦东区的男孩
he ain't got a no good education... but all of a sudden
他没有不好的 教育…但突然之间，
the Eastend boy's got a car, motorbike and he goes to Spain every year
在伦敦东区的男孩有一辆汽车，摩托车 他每年都去西班牙
and whatever
不管
and have I worked for it?
我有工作了吗？
no, I'm here putting bets on
不，我在这里 把赌注
and you think "how does he do it?"
你认为如何 他做的吗？”
and there's a boy, who's he? and whatever
有一个男孩， 他是谁？不管
he's studying to be a professor, he's making up the things
他学习成为一名教授， 他做了的事
where's the education, there's no education in this world
教育的地方，那里的 在这个世界上没有什么教育
it's just one big rat race and you've got to
这是一只大老鼠 比赛，你必须
kill your man next to you to get in front of him
杀死你的人在你旁边 要在他面前
education, when I said "there's no education"
教育，当我说 “没有教育”
yes, there is an education I made a grave mistake in saying that
是的，有一个教育 我说，犯了一个严重的错误
but, I didn't mean to say there's no education as far as academically
但是，我不想说的 教育不尽的学术
yes, there is
是的，有
the area, the environment
区域，环境
and education makes a person have more opportunities in this world
教育使一个人 在这个世界上更多的机会
you know, I mean that's.. that's obvious
你知道，我的意思是 是的。这是显而易见的
Let's talk about the kids.
让我们的孩子说话。
Do you want for them what you had for yourself?
你想他们什么 你有吗？
In terms of schooling and everything?
从学校教育 和所有的一切？
you're talking about.. my childhood five years old upwards to 7, 8, 9
你谈的。我的童年 五岁以上的7，8，9
I had no money, my father had no money
我没有钱，我爸爸没有钱
I wore my brother's clothes for ten years
我穿着我的兄弟 十年的衣服
these hand-me-down's are sort of going on my arms with holes on them
这些方面我失望的是 继续在我的手臂上
I've never had any opportunities to better myself because I was a kid
我从来没有过任何机会 更好的自己，因为我是个孩子
I never knew no better
我不知道更好的
my mum and dad, you know
我的爸爸和妈妈，你知道的
my dad's got.. you know he's.. he couldn't work
我爸爸有..你知道他的。 他不能工作
I'm not making a violin story out of this
我不是一个 小提琴的故事了
I mean, that's the way it was
我的意思是，这样的事
and I'm more stronger
我更坚强
it happened that way I mean, I'm a more stronger person
事情就是这样的 我的意思是，我是一个更强大的人
I appreciate things more now
我很欣赏的东西现在
and now I'm in a position through my job
我现在在一个位置 通过我的工作
you know, to give my kids the life I never had like.. lovely clothes
你知道，给我的孩子们的生活 我从未有过像。可爱的衣服
I go to holidays, you know, I go to Portugal and I go to Spain
我去度假，你知道的， 我去，我去西班牙，葡萄牙
hopefully America next year
希望明年的美国
I mean, I want everything
我的意思是，我想要的一切
I never had to go, you know, on my kids
我没有去，你知道的，我的孩子
to say, you know...
说，你知道的…
let them know the benefits of the nice life and what's it's all about
让他们知道的好处 美好的生活，什么是它的所有有关
they're precious! "oh yes... oh yes... oh yes..."
他们是宝贵的！ “哦，是的…哦，是的…哦，是的……”
they're nuts!
他们都是疯子！
you just have to touch them...
你只需要触摸它们…
yeah, they.. well, they can get what they want, can't they?
是啊，他们..嗯，他们可以得到 他们想要的是什么，不是吗？
If you've got to work for it
如果你已经为它工作
and it's them that can just ask for money and get it
这是他们可以 请买它
and they can buy what they want
他们可以买他们想要的东西
I've learned through driving a cab that people are individuals
我已经通过了驾驶室 那人是个人
whatever they are.. upperclass or, you know, middleclass or..
不管他们是什么..高年级或， 你知道，中产阶级或..
as in my case, you know, an Eastender
在我的情况下，你知道，一个eastender
but
但
I'm only glad, you know, that I've found out the difference at an early age
我只是很高兴，你知道，我已经找到了 在早期的年龄的差异
so i can judge people..
所以我可以判断的人。
on what they are rather than who they are
它们是什么 而不是他们是谁
I'm not a politician so let them worry about what's coming for the next day
我不是政治家，所以让他们担心 接下来的第二天
all I understand is
我理解的是
dogs, prices, girls, knowledge, roads, streets, squares and
狗，价格，女孩，知识， 的道路，街道，广场和
mum and dad and love
爸爸妈妈和爱
that's all I understand that's all I want to understand
这是所有我知道的 我想了解
four and a half fifties, four and a half fifties, four and
四和一半的年代， 四个半岁，四和
At 21 he was earning a bit extra as a bookie's runner at Hackney Wick.
21岁的他是赚了一点额外的 作为一个赌徒的转轮在Hackney灯芯。
What do they call you here?
他们怎么在这里给你打电话吗？
I reckon a pest, or something like that
我估计害虫，或 像那样的东西
I don't mean to make a nuisance of myself
我不想做 讨厌自己
I mean if for other patrons of the place
我的意思是如果其他 这个地方的顾客
they don't want to see a little boy nipping between their feet
他们不想看到一个小 男孩在他们的脚夹
running, putting a bet on here for a face
运行，把 打赌这里的脸
they don't understand, they think "cor what's he doing is he mad?"
他们不理解，他们认为 “肺他在干什么他疯了吗？”
I mean, I walk up there and I order the teas
我的意思是，我走到那里 我要茶
there could be eight people in front of me, I just go...
可能会有八人 在我的前面，我就去…
"can I have a tea please.. tea pleas" five times, "tea please.. tea please.."
“请给我一杯茶好吗。茶请” 五次，“茶请..请茶”。
and they've gotta serve me before them or get rid of me
他们要为我服务 在他们面前，或摆脱我
do you understand?
你听懂了吗？
so that's how you've got to do it
这就是你要做的
I'm in two golf societies
我在两个高尔夫球协会
and each month, all of the members of each society meet to play a game of golf
每个月，所有的成员 每一个社会会打一场高尔夫球
and who are the guys you play with?
谁是 你玩？
well, they are mostly publicans or taxi drivers, you know
嗯，他们大多是税吏 和出租车司机，你知道的
and..
和..
we always end up, you know, have a small bet
我们总是结束了，你知道的， 有一个小的赌注
Do you like the whole social side of it? - only with my mates because
你喜欢它的整个社会的一面？ 只因为我的队友
on a golf course it becomes the very.. snooty type, you know
在高尔夫球场成为 很..傲慢型的，你知道的
I mean, I understand they've got to pay a
我的意思是，我知道他们已经有了 支付
and they don't, you know, really want anyone without any etiquitte
他们不，你知道，真的希望 没有任何人etiquitte
to go on the golf course and ruin their so called golf course, right?
去高尔夫球场和毁灭 他们所谓的高尔夫球场，对吗？
that's good.. great shot.. great shot..
很好.. 伟大的射击。好的照片..
it does get a bit.. a pain sometimes you know when
它确实有一点..有时疼痛 你知道的当
when they keep saying "excuse me sir, are you a member?"
当他们说“对不起先生， 你是会员吗？”
it comes out like that
它是那样
obviously etiquette's etiquette
显然，礼仪的礼仪
so you've got to conduct yourself on these type of courses
所以你要进行 你对这些类型的课程
cause I think..
原因我认为
you're a bit smaller than most people
你小一点 比大多数人
you try and hit the ball hard
你试着打硬球
you've got to just.. it'll get there
你.. 它会
where'd he go? - I'm over here
他去哪儿了？ -我在这里
oh.. I missed that one - unlucky.. keep hold of her
哦。我错过了一个 ――不幸的。保持她的
- it's about an eight to the.. - too much mate.. too much
-它是一个八的.. 有太多的伙计。太多的
no it ain't.. no it ain't.. no.. Ton.. hit an eight
不在这里。真的没什么好看的。没有。 吨。创八
it's definitely an eight - no that's too much club Ken
肯定是八 没有太多的俱乐部肯
- eight, hit an eight - no.. no.. give us a nine mate
-八，达到了八 没有。没有。给我们一九的伴侣
nine, I think that's about right - if you hit a nine, hit it to the right
九，我认为这是正确的 如果你打一九，打到右
that's it.. that's it.. that's perfect..
那是它。那是它。这是完美的。'''
great shot
很棒的投篮
that's a great shot
这是一个伟大的投篮
now I, am a young fella and I've come to you
现在的我，是一个年轻的小伙子 我来给你
I heard that you are a big successful taxi driver - you want advice?
我听说你是一个大的成功 出租车司机-你要建议？
- yes I...
-是的我..
- I've been a film extra now for six years
我是个电影 六年多了
It may not go no futher I mean I'm just..
它可能不会去没有进一步的 我的意思是，我只是..
having acting lessons..
在表演课了。
- you give me the benefit of all of your experience
-你给我的利益 你所有的经验
alright? now you've got to feel pretty big, bigger than me
好吗？现在你已经感觉到了 相当大的，比我大
- just go? - right there! here we go!
-只是去吗？ -就在那里！让我们开始吧。
- tell me son, what do you want to be a cab driver for mate?
告诉我的儿子，你是什么 要为队友一个出租车司机？
- well, make a lot of money you know, have a good life`
-好的，赚了很多钱 你知道，有一个良好的生活`
- son, look at me, I might be a successful business man
的儿子，看着我，我可能是一个 成功的生意人
I might have the suit.. I might have the..
我会服。 我有..
all the holidays in Spain every year but son it's hard work out there mate
所有节日每年在西班牙 但的儿子是很难解决的有配偶
- you're not reaching me yet - not getting to you
你还没有达到我呢 不是让你
- no, you're not getting to me, alright? now be bigger, dominate me, alright?
-不，你不能给我，好吗？ 现在是大的，支配我，好吗？
- son! - yeah?
的儿子！ 是啊？
son, it's a big world out there and obviously I'm not..
的儿子，这是一个很大的世界 那里，显然我不是..
I can't get into it Warren - alright, don't worry
我不能进入沃伦 -好的，别担心
- when I was in The Sweeney and when I was in Churchill: The Wilderness Years
当我在当我和斯威尼 丘吉尔：在旷野里
I see the actors and I thought, like you know
我看到演员 我想，像你知道的
it's not quite easy to act on stage
行动阶段是不太容易的
cause it's you know, you need time and dedication, it's very hard
因为你知道，你需要 时间和奉献精神，是很难的
- son! tell me why do you want to be a taxi driver!
的儿子！告诉我你为什么 想成为一名出租车司机！
well you know you've got success
你知道 你有成功
- don't let.. don't let looks go impressing... I mean, listen
-不要让..别让外表去 留下深刻印象…我的意思是，听
- What excites you about acting?
什么让你兴奋的表演？
I like it, I mean, I think of me self, you know
我喜欢它，我的意思是，我认为 自我，你知道的
I can do that, I still want to have a go of it, I mean nothing for sort of
我能做到，我还想去 它，我的意思是没有什么
fame or fortune or anything like that
名利或类似的东西
big hollywood and bright lights
好莱坞大和明亮的灯光
it's nothing like that, just a side line
不是那样的， 只是一个副线
So, what drives you then through all of these various ambitions?
那么，是什么驱使你然后 通过所有这些不同的野心？
it's a philosophy of not keeping still, I mean..
这是一个哲学不 保持静止，我的意思是..
I'm a very overactive type of person, I mean..
我是一个非常活跃的 型的人，我的意思是..
I like to feel that I don't want to keep still
我觉得我 不想保持安静
because life, you know, don't wait for nobody so you've gotta cram it in
因为生活，你知道，不要等待 没人让你得把它
as much as you can before you're days are numbered
尽你所能 在你的日子屈指可数
I mean, I may be a happy-go-lucky type of fellow, which I am
我的意思是，我可能是一个无忧无虑的 型的人，这我
I'm an Eastender which the attitude is, "allo' mate, alright, how are ya?"
我是一个eastender的态度， “异”的伴侣，好吧，怎么是你？”
type of thing
一类的东西
I wouldn't want to lose that
我不想失去，
How long are you going to be a cab driver?
你多久 要成为一个出租车司机？
Is this what you want to do for the rest of your life?
这是你想要的 做为你的余生？
well, at the moment, I'm very happy driving a cab
好了，此刻，我 很高兴一个计程车司机
but..
但是..
my wife and I always considered owing our own pub
我的妻子和我总是认为 由于我们自己的酒吧
so obviously, I think, within two or three years
所以，我认为，在 两或三年
once I get financially straightened out
一旦我得到财政上的 理顺
I'm going to have a go at being a publican
我要走了 在被一个税吏
and if I don't like it
如果我不喜欢它
say, if I give it a go for a year or even six months
说，如果我给它一个去 年或六个月
if I don't like being a publican
如果我不喜欢 作为一个老板
I'm in a good position to say get rid of the pub and go back to taxi driving
我是一个很好的位置，说摆脱 的酒吧，再去开出租车
I don't want to change because if I change
我不想改变 因为如果我改变
it proves that Tony Walker was all fake
它证明了 托尼沃克都是假的
fifty five to twenty, boys?
五零五到二十，男孩？
- What are the best times for you?
-你的最佳时间是什么时候？
two, two really the best..
两个，两个真的 最好的..
time is when the kids.. the first baby was born
时间是当孩子。 第一个孩子出世
the next one, obviously, Jodi
下一个，很明显，朱迪
but my greatest fulfillment in life
但我最大的满足的生活
when I.. when I rode at Kempton
当我。当我骑在肯普顿
in the same race as Lester Piggott
在同一种族李斯特Piggott
I was a naive, wet behind the ears, apprentice
我是一个天真，湿背后 耳朵，学徒
and the governor told me "you've got to ride son"
和州长告诉我 “你要乘坐的儿子”
"Friday, you've got to lose x-amount of weight"
“星期五，你已经失去 “x-amount重量
which I did.. eight pounds in four days
这是我的。四天八磅
and he says like, I go in there, and they're all there, you know
他说，我去那里， 他们都有，你知道的
I'm part of it
我是它的一部分
all my years, from seven, all my ambition is fulfilled in one moment
我这些年来，从七，我的所有 野心是在一瞬间完成的
when the longfellow comes out and I'm in with him, like in the same..
当朗费罗出来 我和他一样，在相同的。
the starter is calling out to register the names
起动机是调用 要注册的名字
and he'll sortta go like "Piggott, draw, eight.. Walker, draw, sortta ten"
他会sortta像“友谊， 画，八。沃克，画，sortta十”
and your idol, like, you're there and the big man's there, I mean
你的偶像，像，你在那里 和大男人的存在，我的意思是
money in the whole world couldn't buy that proudest day of my life
在全世界的钱不 买最值得骄傲的一天我的生活
which.. my ambition fulfilled to the highest level
这..我的野心 实现的最高水平
and
和
I eventually finished last
我最终完成了最后的
tailed off obviously, but it didn't make any difference to me
下降明显，但 这对我没有任何区别
just to be part of it, be with the man himself
只是它的一部分， 是他自己
couldn't buy it, that was the proudest day of my whole life
不买它，那是 我一生中最值得骄傲的一天
We are going to Africa...
我们要去非洲…
and trying to teach people...
并试图教人…
who are not civilized
谁是不文明的
to be..
是的。
more or less..
更多或更少的。
good
很好
no,  don't want to be a missionary because
不，不要 一个传教士因为
I just can't talk about it to people
我只是不能说话 关于它的人
you know.. I am interested in it myself but..
你知道..我感兴趣的 在它自己，但是..
I wouldn't be very good at it, at all..
我不是很擅长，在所有。
- Yes Sir!
-是的先生！
Mohan Ali
Mohan阿里
Kasim Mahir - Yes Sir!
卡西姆Mahir -是的先生！
Oscar Ali
奥斯卡阿里
Nasril - Yes Sir! Sultan - Yes Sir!
纳斯利尔-是的先生！ 苏丹-是的先生！
Abdul Khair
阿卜杜勒凯尔
- I was working at an insurance company at the time
我是工作在一个 同时保险公司
and I decided to go into teaching without any experience at all
我决定进入教学 没有任何经验
and I didn't think they'd allow somebody to walk off the street into a classroom
我不认为他们会允许某人 走到街上往教室
6 times 3 is 18, shared by 2 is 9, plus 7 is 16, so you put a 16 there
6乘3是18，2是9的共享， 加7是16，所以你将有16
- they were crying out for most teachers, they interviewed me
他们哭了 大多数的老师，他们采访我
they phoned me up the next day and said "would I like the job?"
他们打电话给我第二天 说：“我喜欢的工作？”
I said "yes," within five weeks..
而我答应了。 在五周。
I was in a classroom
我在教室里
they took one look at me and thought it was christmas, I think
他们看了我一眼， 认为这是圣诞节，我想
What's the most enjoyable thing about teaching?
什么是最令人愉快的 关于教学？
just being a part of the pupils advancement
只是一部分 学生的进步
and learning and watching them understand more
学习和看 更多的了解他们
and being more confident
更有信心
then, getting some enjoyment and satisfaction from mathematics
然后，获得一些乐趣 从数学和满意度
After working in the city for three years,
在工作中 三年的城市，
Bruce Started teaching at Tony's old school in the east end of London.
布鲁斯开始在托尼的教学 在伦敦东区老校。
He lives in a local council flat within walking distance of the school.
他生活在一个地方议会平 在学校的步行距离。
Holden, let's hear the present tense of 'evasto'
霍尔顿，让我们听听 目前的evasto“紧张
Evasto, evastas,  evas..
evasto，evastas，伊娃..
evastant
evastant
evastamus, evastatis, evastant
evastamus，evastatis，evastant
yes, speak up
是的，说出来
they don't, sort of, enforce..
他们不，排序，执行的。
being upper class and..
被上层阶级和。
things like that.. at St. Paul's, you know they..
这样的事情.. 在圣保罗，你知道他们。
suggest that you don't have long hair and they do get it cut if..
建议你不要一直 头发会削减如果..
and..
和..
they teach you to be reasonably well mannered
他们教你的是 合理的规矩
but not too sniff on the poorer people
但不要太嗅贫穷的人
When we filmed him at 21, Bruce was in his last year at Oxford reading maths.
当我们拍到他21岁，是布鲁斯的 他在牛津读数学去年。
and you can show that this is irreducible
你可以显示 这是不可约的
then you do a transformation on this polynomial, x=t+2
你做了改造 这个多项式，X = T＋2
- good, that's a nice way of doing it, particularly using Eisenstein down here
-好的，这是一个很好的做法， 特别是用爱森斯坦这里
because his test is very powerful - yes
因为他的测试非常强大 -是
It's so different from your own education
它是如此的与众不同 你自己的教育
where you're teaching now, why?
你现在教，为什么？
general education is.. better for society, I think
通识教育是.. 更好的社会，我想
public schools are divisive
公立学校的分歧
that's with no statement about my education
这是没有声明 关于我的教育
my education was academically excellent
我的教育 成绩优秀
and I am very grateful for it
和我真的很感激
I think there is a class society and I think..
我认为这是一个阶级社会 我想..
public schools may..
公办学校不得的。
help its continuance
帮助它的延续
- see you're in the lead, you see..
-看你的领导，你看..
because DSE Cabs have got profit of
因为DSE出租车有利润
okay? now can you explain that just to Abdul
好吗？现在你可以 解释，只是阿卜杜勒
because I want him to understand what it is..
因为我想让他 理解它是什么。
I don't know whether..
我不知道..
I said, "right, I must do something which is
我说，“好，我必须 做某事是
against what I've been brought up to do" or whatever...
对我的 提出了要做”或什么的…
I don't know, I just found something I find rewarding
我不知道，我只是发现了 我得到的回报
I didn't agree with the conservatives about what they're doing with the
我不同意保守党 “他们在做什么的
black people, you know racial policy
黑人的种族政策，你知道的
Do you have to defend immigration to a lot of people in this area?
你必须捍卫移民 很多人在这方面？
yes, I think you do but
是的，我想你但是
those who say "there are too many coming in" and so on
那些说“太 许多来”等等
I think, really are uneducated about the whole question
我想，真的是没有受过教育的人 关于这个问题
they should see the positive benefits that they are having in this country
他们应该看到积极的好处 他们在这个国家
and see that as a result of all of this immigration
看作为 所有这些移民的结果
they are not being denied opportunities
他们没有被拒绝的机会
it's not the fault of immigrants that there is unemployment
这不是移民的故障 失业的存在
it's part of a political parties responsibility is to explain that
这是一个政党的一部分 责任是解释
and show people what is the more truthful way
向人们展示 是更真实的方式
of representing the situation
代表的情况
none of the parties seem to agree with me
当事人没有 似乎同意我的观点
and I think if I had voted I'd have voted labour
我想如果我投了票 我投了工党
I am about the only socialist in my village
我的唯一 在我村的社会主义
and I go into the pub and..
和我一起去 进入酒馆
sort of expect to stand up and defend all socialist policies
那种想站起来 维护所有的社会主义政策
sort of, this is the village socialist
是的，这是 该村的社会主义
no, village idiot, sorry
不，村 笨蛋，对不起
I just see their lack of opportunities for
我只看到自己的不足 机遇
a lot of people, obviously, unemployment is a great
很多人，很明显， 失业是一个伟大的
feature in many people's lives and many family's lives
在许多人的生命特征 许多家庭的生活
and..
和..
teaching children, sometimes you wonder
教孩子，有时 你想知道
what's going to happen to them?
发生了什么 发生在他们身上？
it seems to me that
在我看来，
the leader of the country at the moment should be one of the most unpopular
目前，这个国家的领导人 应该是一个最受欢迎的
person's in the country
人在这个国家
and yet she gets away with everything, um..
然而，她得到了 一切，嗯..
she.. as far as I can see has done lots of damage
她..就我所看到的 已经做了大量的破坏
and yet..
但是..
nobody, nobody can oppose her
没有人，没有人能反对她
my heart's desire is to see my daddy who is six thousand miles away
我的心渴望见到我爸 谁是六千英里远
and I can remember being happy there I can remember..
我记得快乐有 我能记得的。
also  being miserable because I can remember crying
因为还痛苦 我能记得我哭
- hold steady!
保持稳定！
you know, I always seemed to be beaten on and I could never understand why
你知道，我似乎总是被打败 对，我不明白为什么
Did it give you an overdeveloped sense of authority?
那给你一个过度 权威感？
if you look at society in general, I've always probably
如果你在一般的社会，我 总是有可能
been on the side of authority
对权威的一边
and you know, it's been, it's been..
你知道，这是 是的，这是..
an education learning that authority can be bad
教育学 权威可不好
and.. can be corrupt
和..可以腐败
well my girlfriend is in Africa
我的女朋友在非洲
and I won't... don't think I'll have another chance of seeing her again
我也知道。别以为我会 另一个机会再见到她
Have you go a girlfriend?
你去一个女朋友？
no.. not yet
没有。还没有
I'm sure it will come
我肯定它会
but not yet
但尚未
I think I would very much like to..
我想我会非常喜欢的。
become involved in a family like my own family for a start
参与一个家庭一样 我自己一开始的家庭
that's a need I feel I ought to fulfill and would like to fulfill
这是一个需要我觉得我应该满足 而要实现
and would do it well
会做的很好
I mean, I do think a lot of people think too much about it
我的意思是，我想很多人 想太多
What happened when you burnt your fingers?
出什么事了 当你燃烧你的手指？
I'd rather not talk about it really
我宁可不说 “这真的
well no in fact I don't really mean that
事实上没有我不 说的是真的
I don't mean I don't want to talk about it
我不是说我不 想谈
it's just I'd need quite a long time to think about it really
我只是需要一个相当长的 时间想想真的
I think I possibly get a little serious
我想我可能 有点严重
and uh..
嗯..
don't quite understand the modern..
不太 了解现代的。
sort of..
类的。
way of behaving, the modern manner..
行为方式， 现代的方式。
I think I'm a little old fashioned
我认为我是一个 小小的老式的
at three o' clock I'm going to come and pick you up from Arts
三点我会来 接你从艺术
you'll only have one art lesson
你只会有一节美术课
so if you're art teacher forgets at five to three
如果你的美术老师 忘记在五到三
ask her to say we should be packing away and I'll come and get you
问她说我们应该包装 走开，我会来接你的
So there you were, you went to a posh preparatory school
所以你是，你去 豪华的预备学校
and a major public school and to Oxford
和一个主要的公立学校，牛津
And now, you're in a council flat teaching in this
现在，你在一个 在这平坦的教学委员会
school in the Eastend of London.
在伦敦的伦敦东区的学校。
You don't feel any sense of disappointment?
你不觉得有什么 失落感？
no because what I am trying to do at the moment and achieve is difficult
不是因为我想要做的 目前的实现是困难的
It may not sound difficult in the sense that you could sum up what I do
它可能不是在困难的声音 意识到你可以总结我做什么
quite simply
很简单
But behind all of that, it is very difficult and..
但在所有这一切， 这是非常困难的和。
I certainly find it satisfying achieving successes
我发现它 获得成功的满足
there may come a time
可能会有一个时间
when I decide I can't do it and that's not necessarily a weakness that's..
当我决定我不能这样做，这是 不一定是软弱的。
that may be a strength that you realize
这可能是一种力量，你知道
you can't do it as well as you would wish
你不能这样做 如你所愿
I think the most important thing in the world is everyone should know about God
我认为最重要的事情的 世界上每个人都知道上帝
It all springs from..
这一切都源于..
having God and Christ I suppose
我想有神和基督
that.. you try do that as best as posttible and let that
那。你试着这样做 最好的posttible让
lead your actions in life
你的行为在生活中的铅
Does it sadden you when you meet people who don't believe in Christianity?
它使你当你遇见的人 那些不相信基督教吗？
yes, if they dismiss it casually, if they dismiss it
是的，如果他们解雇 随便，如果他们解雇
as just being something..
只是一些东西。
"well we know about that, we got a bit about that at school
“我们知道， 我们在学校有一点，
and it doesn't really mean very much"
这并不意味着太多”
then it does sadden me because it's much much more than that
然后它让我感到难过因为 它比其他的更多
What is it about that's important to you?
它说的是什么 对你重要吗？
well, the belief in..
嗯，是信仰
the belief in goodness and in love as being two
在上帝的信仰 和爱是两个
well.. great positive forces in that..
好的。在重大的积极力量..
you know people..
你知道的人。
well, just the simple belief like a good act is never wasted
嗯，只是简单的信念 像一个好的行为是不会白费的
certainly you can observe somebody when they are seven
当然你可以观察 当他们七人
and identify particular things which maybe are then always with them..
独特的东西 也许是那总是与他们。
whatever else happen to them
无论什么发生在他们身上
people possible say I am little to innocent at times or naive
人可能说我是什么 有时天真无辜的
I used to get worried about this and think
我常常担心 这与思考
perhaps I ought not to be taken in or deceived or..
也许我不应该 上当或欺骗或..
I'm not talking about love now, I'm just talking about generally speaking
我不是在谈论爱情，我 只是说一般来说
but um..
但是，嗯..
I feel that's a strength in a way
我觉得这是一个强度
if there are people who are willing to trust
如果有人 愿意相信
then..
然后。
we should be encouraged
我们应该鼓励
Tell me, do you have any boyfriends Suzi?
告诉我。是不是 有男朋友苏茜吗？
Ummm..
嗯..
yes -Tell me about him?
可以 跟我说说他的情况吧？
well, he lives up in Scotland and I think he's thirteen
嗯，他生活在苏格兰 我认为他是十三
and I'm rather lonely up there because he usually goes to school
我宁愿孤独的存在 因为他通常去学校
but we usually play till about half past six when he comes home from school
但我们通常玩到一半 过去的六当他从学校回家
then we go in and then..
然后我们去然后..
he goes home to do his homework
他回家做作业
Have you got any boyfriends Suzi?
你有男朋友苏茜吗？
What is your attitude towards marriage? For your self?
什么是你的态度 婚姻？你的自我？
Well, I don't know I haven't given it a lot of thought
嗯，我不知道我没有给它一个 很多想法
because I'm very very cynical about it
因为我非常怀疑它
but then, you know, you get a certain amount of faith restored in it
但是，你知道，你一定 信心恢复它的量
well, I mean, I've got friends who've
嗯，我的意思是，我有朋友谁是
and their parents are happily married and so it does put faith back into you
和他们的父母结婚了 所以它把信心回到你
but me, myself, I'm very cynical about it
但是，我，我， 我很怀疑
we were friends for about two years
我们大约两年的朋友
Rupert and Suzi we're married five year ago.
鲁伯特和苏茜我们 五年前结婚。
and.. I think the nice thing was that we new each other very well before
和..我认为最好的事情是 我们新的彼此非常之前
we knew quite a lot of the faults of..
我们知道很多 故障的..
each other
对方
which I think's very important
我认为这是非常重要的
I don't sort of sit down and think, you know, analyze marriage
我不是那种坐下来想一想， 你知道，分析婚姻
it's not something I've had to come up and think about
这不是我 来想想
or that I was going to get married
或者，我要结婚了
and I have no desire to at the moment
我不想 此刻
I think.. twenty is far too young
我想。二十是太年轻
I suppose twenty-two is considered quite young
我想二十二 被认为是非常年轻
I felt it was the right time
我觉得是时候了
I don't see what I would have gained by waiting another three years
我不知道我会 等待另一个三年了
What gave you that feeling?
是什么让你有那样的感觉吗？
I just felt I was doing the right thing
我只是觉得我 做正确的事
which as you said was extrodinary when..
这是你说的 是巨大的时候。
only eighteen months before I was very anti it
只有十八个月 以前我是很反对它
I came to London when I left school after Paris
我来到伦敦时 巴黎之后我离开学校
and at the moment I could never live in the country I am happier down here
此刻，我活不下去 在中国我很高兴到这里
the country is nice for four days and you can go for healthy long walks
这个国家是很好的四天 你可以走健康散步
but I Imean.. I could never live up their now
但我是说..我可以 决不辜负他们的现在
They live in a small village near Bath
他们住在一个小村庄附近的浴
where Rupert is a partner in a firm of solicitors.
鲁伯特是一个 在一家律师事务所的合伙人。
I had seven years up in London I suppose it was fantastic but I just had enough
我有七年在伦敦，我想 这真是太棒了但我就已经足够了
it's a much slower way of life down here and I'd had enough of the rat race
这是一个慢得多的生活方式了 在这里，我有足够的“老鼠赛跑
when I get married I'd like to have two children
我结婚时，我 喜欢有两个孩子
I'm not very children minded at the moment
我不在孩子的头脑 的时刻
and I don't know if I ever will be
我不知道我会
What do you think about them?
您认为如何呢？
well, I don't like babies
嗯，我不喜欢孩子
What was the biggest shocks to you
什么是你最大的冲击
when you were suddenly confronted
当你突然遇到
with a small baby that you had to be responsible for?
有一个小宝宝，你 曾负责？
panic set in, I think
恐慌，我认为
that I wasn't going to be able to cope
我不会 能够应付
Do you want a nanny to look after them? Or, do you want to look after them?
你想要一个保姆来照顾他们？ 或者，你想照顾他们？
I want a nanny to look after them
我需要一个保姆来照看他们
I felt that we'd taken the decision to bring a child into this world
我觉得我们会决定 把一个孩子带到这个世界
and I feel that I wanted to bring him up, not somebody else
我觉得我想带 他，不是别人
I thought it's my responsibility to start him off
我认为这是我的 的责任，他开始
whether that will make a difference to how he turns out, I don't know
是否会影响 他是怎么发现的，我不知道
I just felt I wanted to do it
我只是觉得我要做的
Is it everything you wanted?
这是你想要的一切？
for the moment, yes I mean, I don't think I'll have any more
那一刻，是的 我的意思是，我不认为我会有更多的
the reason, that I'll get pleasure out of these two
的原因，我会 得到快乐的这两个
but I can't see me going on and on and on
但是我不能看到我 进行下去
with sort of four or five children
有四或五个孩子般
I think I'd feel that I'd want to move on and try and do something else
我想我会觉得我想离开 在尝试做其他事情
when I leave this school I'm down for Heathfield and South of Amena
当我离开这所学校我 下来的希思菲尔德和南阿美
and then maybe I may want to go to a university
然后我想 上大学
but I don't know which one yet
但我不知道是哪一个呢
I'd like to do..
我想做的。
a course on typing or something like that
课程分型 或类似的东西
I left school when I was sixteen and went to Paris
我离开学校的时候我 十六去巴黎
went to secretarial college and got a job
去秘书 大学找到了一份工作
What made you decide to `leave school and go to Paris?
是什么让你决定 `离开学校，去巴黎？
I just wasn't interested in school and just wanted to get away
我只是不感兴趣的学校 只是想离开
And why did you choose Paris?
你为什么选择巴黎？
I don't know, it was my parents really
我不知道，这是我的父母真的
now I've got to a stage in my life where I've got to make my own decisions
现在我已经在我的生命中的一个阶段 我得自己做决定
you've got to learn to fend for yourself one day
你得学学 保护自己的一天
I went to prep school boarding when I was nine
我去补习学校 登机时我九岁
Rupert went at eight and the both of us hated it
鲁伯特就在八 和我们都讨厌它
I hated my prep school
我讨厌我的预备学校
I just feel it's too young to send a child off
我只是觉得太 年轻的送一个孩子了
and we both feel that we would never send Thomas and Oliver off
我们都觉得我们 永远不会把托马斯和奥利弗
probably maybe until they're thirteen
也许也许直到他们十三
I think eight is much too young
我觉得八太年轻了
so we will definitely keep them at home
所以我们绝对会让他们在家里
Do you still want to send them in the private sector to school?
你还想给他们 在私营部门去学校吗？
I think we will, yes
我认为我们可以，是的
but.. as I said not until they are thirteen
但是..我说不是 直到十三
Why do you choose the private sector opposed to the state?
你为什么选择 私营部门的反对国家？
I suppose it's what we had, it's what we know
我想这是什么 我们有，这是我们所知道的
I think both of us probably were very sheltered
我想我们两个 可能很隐蔽
it's only having been abroad that you can appreciate more
它只在国外 你可以欣赏更多
that people are very different cultures are different
那人非常不同 文化是不同的
but I think as I was growing up I think probably I was far too sheltered
但是我觉得我长大了我 大概是我太庇护
What do you think about making this program?
你的意思如何 制作这个节目吗？
I think it's just ridiculous, I don't see any point in doing it
我认为这是荒谬的，我 不知道在做任何一点
I've been very lucky up to a certain point but everyone has their bad times
我很幸运在一定 但是每个人都有自己的坏的时间点
I'm really just beginning and I'm really young and..
我真的只是开始 我真的很年轻的。
and I'll probably have a lot worse that what I've been through now
我可能会更糟 我已经通过了
when you're a child you always think how nice
当你是个孩子的时候 你总是想如何好
it would be to be grown up and independent..
这将是 长大了，独立了。
but there are times when I wish I was three again
但有时期 当我希望我三次
It just seems a miracle to me that when I last saw you at twenty one you were..
它似乎只是一个奇迹我时 上次我在二零一你看见你
nervous, you were chain smoking, you were uptight and now you seem happy.
紧张，你抽烟， 你紧张，你现在看起来很开心。
What's happened to you over these past seven years?
怎么了你 在过去的七年？
I suppose Rupert
我想鲁伯特
I'll give you some credit
我会给你一些信用
I'm now chain smoking
现在我抽烟
no, I didn't know where I was going at twenty one
不，我不知道在哪里 我会在二零一
I mean, I suppose I thought I was reasonably happy at twenty one
我的意思是，我想我想我 二零一快乐
but I had no kind of direction, no..
但是我没有种方向，号。
I obviously hadn't found what I'd wanted
显然我没有 找到我要的
I don't think most people have at twenty one
我不认为大多数人 在二零一
you're still very very young
你还很年轻
As a teenager Suzi spent her school holidays on her father's estate
作为一个少年苏子度过了她的学校 在她父亲的地产的假期
in Scotland
在苏格兰
What sort of things do you do?
什么样的事情吗？
ride, swim, play tennis, ping-pong
骑马，游泳，打网球，乒乓球
I might play croquet
我会玩槌球
things like that
这样的事情
What about the social life?
社会生活是什么样的？
what in Perthshire? it's quite fun
什么在佩思郡？这很有趣
well with any child going through their parents
任何孩子顺利 通过他们的父母
spitting up at age fourteen, you're at a very vulnerable age
随地吐痰，十四岁， 你在一个非常脆弱的年龄
age and it does cut you up but..
年龄也削减了你但..
nut you know, you get over it, it's not..
果你知道， 你得克服它，它不是。
There's no point in them staying together for me, because it was worse
没有必要住 在为我，因为它是更糟的
I mean, the rides...
我的意思是，游乐设施…
it's worse
更糟糕的是
if two people can't live together there's no point making themselves
如果两人不能在一起 有使自己没有一点
my father died three years ago
我父亲三年前去世了
it's very hard to describe to somebody how you just take the loss
它描述一个人很难 你如何把损失
It is terribly hard and even now I still can't believe my father's not here
这是非常困难的，即使现在我仍然 不敢相信我爸爸不在这里
it's still sinking in I think even after two and a half years.
它仍然是沉在我认为 即使经过两年半。
he was off in Scotland
他是在苏格兰开
It was in that very bad winter of '81
这是非常糟糕的冬天，81
and we were literally snowed in and I couldn't get out
我们是从字面上了 我不能滚出去
and it was three weeks before Thomas was born and..
这是三个星期前 托马斯是出世的。
and I wasn't allowed to fly, no airline would take me
我不能飞， 没有航空公司会把我
and the trains were blocked from the snow
和火车 阻止雪
and so I couldn't get there
所以我不能去那里
and I feel..
我觉得..
I still feel guilty that I didn't try and um..
我仍然感到内疚 我不想..
get myself out of here to go, but..
让我离开这里去，但是..
you know, when you're told you could endager a
你知道，当你 告诉你一个可能危害
babies life, you have to rather sit.. sit still
婴儿的生命，你必须 而坐。静静地坐着
the death of one of your close family is probably something you don't ever
你的一个亲密的家庭成员的死亡 也许你不曾
get over and it's a different kind of
摆脱，这是一种完全不同的
problem than anything else
问题比任何其他
and it is hard to come to terms with
它是硬来
And it was really last year that it sunk in
这是真的 去年，中了
that he really wasn't around anymore
他真的不在了
What do you want most out of life?
你最想要什么样的生活？
to be happy, and get on with life
要快乐，继续生活
I mean, I don't want to just sit back and let it all whiz past
我的意思是，我不想坐下来 让这一切过去的高手
I mean, you don't know how long you've got your life for
我的意思是，你不知道你有多长 让你的生活
you know, you could get run over by a bus tomorrow
你知道，你可以得到跑 明天的公共汽车
so you've got to make the most of it while you've got it
所以你要充分利用它 当你拥有它
Do you have any fears for the future? For yourself?
你害怕什么 对于未来？为你自己？
no, not so much for myself at all
不，不是为了自己在所有
I feel if I was going to have fallen by the wayside, I'd have done it by now
我觉得如果我去了 路边，我就
I think probably I'm..
我想我。
too staid now to do that
现在这样做太呆板
but maybe I'm wrong
但也许我是错的
when I grow up
当我长大了
I'd like to..
我想..
find out all about the moon and all that
找出所有关于月亮和所有
At seven, Nick, a farmer's son was at a one room village school in the Dales.
七岁时，尼克，一个农民的儿子是在 在山谷的一间乡村学校。
I said I was interested in physics and chemistry
我说我很感兴趣 在物理学和化学
well, I'm not going to do that here
嗯，我不想这样做
At 14, he was going to a Yorkshire boarding school,
在14，他要 约克郡的一个寄宿学校，
and at 21, was reading physics at Oxford.
在21，是 在牛津攻读物理学。
- plug it in - we'll give it a whirl
塞在 我们要给它一个旋转
So what career are you going to pursue?
所以你的事业去追求？
It depends on whether I'll be good enough to do what I want to really do
这取决于我是否会好的 做我想做的
I would like, if I can, to do research
我想，如果我可以， 做研究
He is now in America, an assistant professor at the University of Wisconsin
他现在在美国，一个助理 威斯康星大学的教授
earning 30,000 dollars a year
年收入30000美元
The gas in these experiments is at a temperature
气体在这些实验 是在温度
comparable with that of the sun
媲美的太阳
whereas in a power reactor it would be maybe 10 times
而在动力反应堆会 也许10次
the temperature of the sun and we're trying to induce that gas to fuse
太阳的温度和我们 试图诱导气体融合
the fusion reaction gives off energy and produces the power that would
聚变反应放出的能量和 产生的电力将
be turned into electrical energy and sent out to the consumer
被转化为电能 并发送给消费者
how hot is it in there?
里面有多热吗？
in there, it's at about ten million degrees
在那里，它在 一千万度
Nick is a Nuclear Physicist.
尼克是一位核物理学家。
He's using these high temperatures to fuse atoms.
他利用这些高 温度保险丝原子。
To try to produce energy which is free from radioactivity.
为了产生能量 这是无放射性。
..has to be precisely coordinated with the positive..
..必须精确协调 与积极的。'''
I finished my degree in physics and I went on to do a p.h.d.
我完成了我的学位 我又做了一个公共卫生博士
and having got the p.h.d.
有了公共卫生博士
after it took two and a half years to get that which was relatively quick
经过了两年半的时间 得到的是相对快速的
I went to work at
我去工作
the United Kingdom Atomic Energy Authorities Cullum Laboratory
联合国原子能 当局卡勒姆实验室
which is where they do fusion research
这是哪里 他们做的融合研究
and that is what I've been aiming to do throughout my p.h.d.
这就是我一直 为了做在我的公共卫生博士
but I..
但我。
but I found when I got there that I got a big shock when I found that my
但我发现当我到达那里时，我得到了 一个大的冲击时，我发现我的
standard of living went down when I started work
生活水平 当我开始工作了
so when some people here offered me a job I thought this might be
所以当有人在这里了 我的工作，我想这可能是
a good opportunity to go somewhere else where the research environment
一个很好的机会去别的地方 在研究环境
was a bit more vigorous
一位精力充沛
so I came here in November of 1982, into a blizzard
所以我来到这里 1982十一月，在一个暴风雪
the university is substantially different from an English university
大学基本上是 不同于英国大学
for several reasons
有几个原因
it's a much bigger university
这是一个更大的大学
Oxford had 10,000 people, this has 40,000 people
牛津有10000人， 这40000人
I guess the mixture of people who come here are different
我猜的混合物的人 这里是不同的
a far bigger fraction of the population go to university here
人口的一个更大的部分 去大学
Oxford is full of people who really are trying to prove something, I suppose
牛津有很多人真的是 你想证明什么，我想
or be something
或是什么
a lot of people with social or intellectual pretensions
许多社会或人 知识要求
you're less aware of that sort of thing here
你不知道 在这里，这种事情
On the other hand, the American system
另一方面，美国的制度
is much more like the comprehensive system
更像是 综合系统
England would set out to try and be; it takes many more people
英格兰将着手尝试； 它需要更多的人
and gets a huge section of the population
得到一个巨大的部分 的人口
to a level where they're really
到一个水平，他们是真的
technically very competent and can go out and make Silicon Valley work
技术能力非常强，可以去 并使硅谷工作
Do you have a girlfriend?
你有女朋友吗？
I don't want to answer that
我不想回答
I don't want to answer those kinds of questions
这些问题
I thought that one would come up because when I was...
我认为一个会 因为当我…
when I was doing the other onensomebody said "what do you think about girls?"
当我做了其他的onensomebody 说：“你怎么想呢？”
I said, "I don't answer questions like that" is that the reason you're asking?
我说，“我不回答这样的问题 “是你问的原因？
oh, I thought so
哦，我是这么认为的
the best answer would be to say that I dont answer questions like that but..
最好的答案是说 我想回答这样的问题，但是。
It's what I said when I was seven and it's still the most sensible but I mean
这就是我说的我是七的时候 它仍然是最明智的但我的意思
what about them?
他们是怎么样的？
Nick was only 17 when I first met him and I knew he was a nice person
尼克只有17岁时，我第一次见到他 我知道他是一个很好的人
I find him very attractive, and..
我发现他很有吸引力，而且..
he uses intelligence in his relationship with me which is very important
他把智力的关系 我是非常重要的
a lot of people can be very bright..
很多人会很亮。
Nick and Jackie met while they were students at Oxford
尼克和杰基相遇时 是学生在牛津
Jackie is doing a post-graduate course in Business Studies
杰基做的一个研究生 在商业课程
What about you Nick? Why did you marry Jackie?
你怎么样呢？ 你为什么嫁给杰基吗？
Because she's..
因为她的。
I find her attractive, she's bright and independent and..
我觉得她很有魅力， 她很聪明和独立的。
If you've been somebody who..
如果你已经有人了。
that had fixed ideas of a woman's role in marriage
有固定的想法 婚姻中的女人的角色
that meant dinner on the table at 6 every evening..
这意味着在晚餐 表6每一个黄昏。
didn't I tell you about that?
我没告诉你吗？
I think we would've had problems or if one of us had not wanted children
我想我们会有问题 如果我们不想要孩子
when I grow up
当我长大了
I'd like to..
我想..
find out all about the moon and all that
找出所有的 月亮和所有
Where did you get all this brain-power from?
你去哪儿了 所有这些脑电？
all this brain-power? I don't know, did it just happen?
所有这些脑？ 我不知道，只是发生的？
all this brain-power.. that's a hard one to answer
这些大脑的力量。 这是个很难回答的问题
because first I have to accept that I've got all this brain-power
因为我必须先接受 我已经得到所有的脑力
and that's not the sort of thing I tend to go around saying
这不是那种事情 我倾向于去说
but I've always been interested in, from a very early age in..
但是我一直有兴趣在， 从很早的时候..
technical or scientific things
技术或科学的东西
when I was very young, I had a picture-book about "the planets"
在我很小的时候， 我有一个关于“行星的图画书”
and I thought this was wonderful and I've just been..
我认为这是美好的 我已经..
interested in that sort of thing and reading technical or scientific material
这一类的事情感兴趣， 阅读科技材料
for a long, long time
很长，很长的时间
I was the only child my age in my village
我是唯一的孩子 在我的村庄，我的年龄
but I mangaged to spend my time talking to adults who were around
但我设法度过我的时间 跟周围的成年人谁
If one is wandering down a country lane
如果一个流浪的小路
there is an awful lot to look at in the world around you
有看很多 在你周围的世界
I remember looking at various natural phenomena
我记得我 在各种自然现象
and being intrigued to try and understand what made them tick1
并想尝试 了解是什么让他们tick1
one time I was particularly wrapped up in how a particular cloud
有一次我特别包 在一个特定的云
which was a very unusual shape you know, and how did that work?
这是一个非常不寻常的形状 你知道的，以及这是如何工作的呢？
and that was the sort of thing that made me want to go further into
这是那种事 我想进一步探讨
natural sciences
自然科学
I think that if I'd been in a city I'd probably would've had more interaction
我想，如果我在一个城市，我 可能会有更多的相互作用
with people and might have developed more..
与人 也可能有更多。
skills in dealing with other kids
在处理与其他孩子的技能
trying to become a reasonably well-adjusted person was for me
想成为一个合理的 正常的人是我
a bit of a struggle for awhile I was given a fantastic opportunity
有一段时间的斗争 我得到了一个绝佳的机会
when I went to university and that really saved my bacon
当我去大学 这可真是救了我的培根
They'd like to..
他们会喜欢的。
to come out for a holiday in the country, we we like..
去度假 在这个国家，我们像。
when I'd like to have a holiday in the town
当我想 在镇上的一个假期
I've been to Leeds a couple of times and.. I haven't been to Manchester
我一直到利兹几次 和..我没有去过曼彻斯特
I went to London with the other...
我和其他去伦敦…
when you did the first program but that's the only time I've been..
当你的第一程序 但这是我唯一的一次..
What attracts you about America?
是什么吸引你喜欢美国吗？
it's an exciting place to be, there's a lot going on
这是一个令人兴奋的地方， 有很多事要做
in terms of research, and other things
在研究方面，和其他的东西
but I really came here to do research but..
但我真的来了 在这里做研究，但..
there are more opportunities and just a general feeling of more going on
有更多的机会和 只是一个普通的更多的事情，感觉
than I had previously
比我以前
this place is less hidebound, less bureaucratically tied down
这个地方是少一些死板， 更少的官僚束缚
so it's much easier to go out and get things done than in England
所以它很容易出去 和把事情做得比英国
Do you get lonely here?
你在这里感到寂寞吗？
You just tend to get stuck here into your
你只会 困在这里为你
everyday routine and you don't think about it
每天的例行公事 你不想它
when you call home, then you realize how far away you are
当你打电话回家， 然后你意识到你是多么遥远
and now it seems acute because our families are getting older
现在看来，急性因为 我们的家庭正在长大
even if you think in terms of seeing them
即使你认为 看到他们的条款
once every two years
每2年一次
- that's not so many times, is it - you're thinking only about ten times
-那不是很多次，它是 你只想着十倍
and that's awful, when you think in those terms and realize...
这是可怕的，当你觉得 在这些条件和实现…
you really are in exile
你真的是在流放
Does this put a pressure on your relationship?
这是把压力 在你的关系？
no, I think it binds us together
不，我认为它把我们绑在一起
because we just have one another over here
因为我们有 另一个在这里
In 21, some of the people were saying
21，一些人说
that they felt it was immoral to emigrate
他们认为这是 不道德的移民
immoral to leave.
不道德的离开。
Do you have any feelings about that since you're the one whose left?
你有什么感觉 因为你的离开？
in my position
我的位置
I don't feel that I'm letting England down
我不觉得 我让英格兰失望
because I don't think that England particularly wanted me there
因为我不认为英格兰 特别是在需要你
doing what I was doing
做我在做什么
It had trained me marvelously
它培养了我地
I'd gone through a wonderful educational system
我经历了一个美妙的 教育系统
particularly Oxford was a fantastic experience socically
尤其是牛津 一个神奇的经验socically
again, it was a great place to try and develop emotionally
再次，这是一个尝试的好地方 发展感情
and the academic standards there are absolutely superb
有学术标准 绝对是最好的
having trained in a very academic fashion there
在训练中的一个 很有学术时尚
and I then went out to try and do something with all that training and
然后我去尝试做的 所有的培训和东西
found that society just wasn't terribly interested in what I was trying to do
发现社会并不可怕 感兴趣，我想做的
so how could I feel that I'm betraying a country when it doesn't want me to do
可我怎么觉得我背叛 一个国家时，它不想让我做的
to do what it's trained me to do?
做它的训练，我做的吗？
a really big issue for us at the moment is
一个真正的大问题 我们现在是
how we're going to manage to have kids and run two careers
我们如何能有孩子 和运行两个职业
we don't want to
我们不想
miss out on the chance of having a significant career,
错过机会 有一个有意义的职业生涯，
and we don't want to miss out on the chance to have kids
我们不想错过 对机会有孩子
and to be involved with them
并能与他们
but in those early formative years, would you be happy for your children
但在那些早期的童年， 你会为你的孩子是快乐的
to be brought up by Jackie
是杰基提出的
and Jackie not be able to give them her full attention?
杰基无法给他们 她全部的注意力？
well it's not.. that's putting it in a rather  strange way - it's not just me
这不是..这是放在一个 而奇怪的方式-不只是我
I.. this is...1
I.。这是……1
this is an area...I pay lip service to the idea of equal shares on this as well
这是一个地区……我耍嘴皮子 平分秋色的想法也在这
and it remains to be seen if I would actually live up to my intention
但仍有待观察，如果 我会辜负我的意图
there are several things, I think, to be said here
有几件事，我想， 可以说在这里
if we both work in academia, that will make life much easier because
如果我们都工作在学术界， 这将使生活更容易，因为
as things are at the moment in the States, if you have a computer at home
就目前的 状态，如果你家里有一台电脑
you can come in to teach and to give office hours to your students
你可以来教给 办公时间你的学生
but you can work
但是你可以工作
half of the day from home
从家里白天的一半
but I don't want to be the person left behind while Nick flies in
但我不想成为的人 留守Nick苍蝇
and shares an adult life with his children
与股票的成年生活 与自己的孩子
at college and working, I want to be there to
在大学和工作， 我想在那里
Is she difficult?
她是困难的？
at times, yes
有时，是的
whenever we have an argument she does have a tendency to explode, I suppose
每当我们有争论她 有爆炸的倾向，我想
to get, no to get really miserable about it, and not..
得到的，不到真正的 不幸的是，并不是..
we've only been married four years
我们已经结婚四年了
anything could happen
任何事情都有可能发生
we could easily drift apart there are so many pressures on people
我们可以很容易地分开 有这么多人的压力
you just have to work at it
你只需要在它的工作
and that's why it's important that you have the same ideas
这就是为什么它是重要的 你有相同的想法
that you want the same kind of life
你想同的生命
when we were in England, our big source of arguments was money
我们在英格兰的时候， 我们的大来源的论点是钱
we were always squabbling about money but that one, mercifully..
我们总是为钱 但是，谢天谢地了。
it seems to have gone away pretty well, we still disagree
它似乎已经消失的很好， 我们仍然不同意
but it isn't a major source of rows
但它不是一个主要的源行
A person with one million pounds is not going to be muvh
一个一百万磅的人 是不是要多
is not goint to be more unhappy than a person with two million pounds
是不是会更不开心 比一个二百万磅的人
I've never really been aiming for money
我真的从来没有 针对钱
and that's curiously enough why it was such a surprise that..
这是奇怪的是 为什么这是一个奇怪的。
it really surprised me when I found that my standard of living mattered to me
这真的让我吃惊，我发现 对我来说最重要的我的生活标准
when I finished University and I found that I couldn't afford
我读完大学，当我发现 我买不起
what I'd been able understood I could afford as a student
我能理解我 可以作为一个学生
It suddenly caught up with me for the first time in my life
它突然抓住了我 这是我生命中第一次
that I really did care about how much moneyI was getting
我真的做了多少照顾 moneyi越来
and it didn't ever occur to me that I would
它不曾想到我 我会
if I could change the world, I'd change it into a diamond
如果我能改变世界， 我想把它换成一个钻石
I'd like to think, I'm hoping that I might do at some stage
我想，我希望 我可能会在某个阶段
but I don't really think that I've done anything that you can call
但我真的不认为我做的 你可以打电话
a great success, I mean..
一个巨大的成功，我的意思是..
It would seem really ridiculous to any of my friends who watch this if I said
似乎任何真可笑 我的朋友看如果我说
"Christ, aren't I a great success, look at me"
“基督，不是我 巨大的成功，看我的”
When I first met you, I remember I thought this was very idealistic
当我第一次见到你，我记得 我认为这是非常理想的
but it was rather interesting
但它是很有趣的
when I asked you why you're working on fusion
当我问你为什么 你工作的融合
you said that you wanted to save the world
你说你 想拯救世界
It was a - I think that's a bit embarrasing now
这是一个我认为是 有点尴尬了
but I don't think you'd feel the same way about something that
但我不认为你会觉得 有关的东西，同样的方式
you didn't feel mattered
你不觉得很重要
that's right
这是正确的
I picked it because I thought it really was something that could be
我拿起它，因为我觉得它真的 是一些可以
useful to people
有用的人
hopefully.. eventually..
希望..最后..
yes, it would be a disappointment if I didn't..
是的，这将是一个 如果我对你失望。
achieve very much but I'm not worrying about it very much
实现非常多 但我担心的不是很
I've just got to go out and make it happen
我刚刚去了 让它发生
I don't think you want to go to university
我不想你 去上大学
if you want to be an astronaut
如果你想成为一名宇航员
What?
什么？？
changed my mind completely of course
我改变主意了 全面的课程
I think it was just the
我认为这只是
imagination a 7 year old has
想象一个7岁的
I might be living in cloud cuckoo land, you know
我可能生活在 世外桃源，你知道的
mum and dad might say, "no son"
妈妈和爸爸会说，“无子”
"that's not life, you don't get a job you like"
“那不是生活， 你没有得到一个你喜欢的工作”
I'd like to think I could
我想我可以
teachers are undervalued
教师被低估
The whole system is beginning to crumble
整个系统 开始瓦解
you know, people outside of it don't realize that, but it is
你知道，外面的人 它不知道，但它是
and it's ..
这是..
very disillusioning, you know, you don't feel you're getting anywhere
非常令人失望的，你知道的， 你不觉得你的地方
and of course the money as well
当然，金钱也
which, whatever the papers tell you, is abysmal
其中，无论报纸 告诉你，太糟糕了
Peter left his comprehensive school in Liverpool
彼得把他的综合 学校在利物浦
and at 21 was studying history at London University
在21的研究 伦敦大学的历史
living in student digs
住在学校宿舍
the facts were
事实是
that I'm particularly an intelligent person, just reasonably, I suppose
我是一个智能 人，只要合理，我想
I'm not a genius, I just went to college
我不是天才，我只是去上大学
on three reasonable A levels
三一个合理的水平
and just didn't do very much work for three years, just did the bare minimum
只是没有做很多工作 三年来，做赤裸的最小
turned up to lectures, wrote a few essays
出席讲座， 写了几篇
you get a degree for it and it was a joke really
你拿到学位了 这是一个笑话，真的
once Carolyn Stepford said she loved me
卡洛琳说，她每天一次 爱我
and I'm going to marry her wehn I grow up
我要娶她 当我长大了
doesn't appeal to me at all at the moment.. I've just gone twenty
我不喜欢在所有 在一瞬间。我刚去了二十
I haven't even been abroad yet in my life so..
我还没有去过国外 然而，在我的生活..
there's no way I'm going to get settled down
我不可能 要安定下来
what was it about Peter that you fell in love with?
它是关于什么的彼得 你爱上了吗？
who said anything about love? I don't..
谁在说什么 爱？我不行。
we have a very much the same attitude, much the same general attitude
我们有一个非常相同的 的态度，同样的一般态度
to life, even though we're very different in personality
为了生活，即使我们 性格很不同
and in the things we like to do
在我们喜欢做的事情
what is it about his personality that attracted you?
这是关于什么的他 个性吸引了你？
nothing really, I don't know..
真的没什么，我不知道。
not..
不..
not a great deal
不是一个伟大的交易
Peter and Rachel have been married four years
彼得和瑞秋 结婚四年了
and met at teacher training college
遇到在教师培训学院
they have just bought their first home
他们刚买了他们的第一个家
a terraced house in the center of Leicester
一间屋子 莱斯特的中心
they both have careers
他们都有职业
Peter teaches in a comprehensive school
彼得在综合学校教
Rachel in a college of further education
瑞秋在继续教育学院
there are two risks, either for one of us to follow the other around
有两种可能，要么 我们跟随其他周围
and therefore, perhaps become frustrated
因此，也许变得沮丧
and dissatisfied that you didn't
不，你没有
initially follow your own line, or your own individual wants
最初，走你自己的路， 或您自己的个人欲望
or there's the risk that you take that you perhaps do have to part sometimes
或有风险，你拿了 你也许有部分有时
for jobs or whatever
为工作或什么的
or, for what you particularly want to do
或者，你特别想做的事
I think the latter risk is much more worth taking
我认为后者的风险 更值得
So you would be prepared to part?
所以你将准备的一部分吗？
Yeah, I mean obviously there is an element of compromise
是的，我的意思是很明显的 这是一种妥协的元素
otherwise why get married?
否则为什么要结婚？
And do you have any plans for children?
你对孩子们有什么计划吗？
not at the moment, no
目前没有，没有
but us, we haven't really thought abou it seriously
但是我们，我们真的没有 想一下严重
Why's that?
为什么？
well, it's because we've both got you know..
嗯，那是因为我们 都有你知道..
things we'd still prefer to be doing you know, if you have children..
我们还是喜欢做的事 你知道，如果你有孩子。
that immediatlely limits you
那immediatlely限制你
I don't want to be limited yet
我不想被限制而
if you choose to have a family, then you also have a responsibility to children
如果你选择了一个家庭，那么你 也有责任的孩子
so you know... it's a very difficult decision
所以你知道… 这是一个非常艰难的决定
and although I think most liberated men
虽然我认为最解放的人
would say that they too are involved in that decision
他们也会说 参与决策
I think ultimately the responsibility still comes down on the woman's head
我认为最终的责任 仍然是女人头上
is Peter liberated?
彼得解放的吗？
well I think a lot of men such as Peter like to think they're liberated
我想很多人如彼得 想他们解放了
and I'm not in any way..
我不以任何方式..
saying that he's not
他说他不是
but I think when it comes to the crunch
但我认为，当危机来临时，
you know, the absolute crunch...
你知道的，绝对的危机…
are you going to give up your job to look after these children?
你要放弃你的工作 照看这些孩子？
then I think it more often than not
那么我认为这更多的往往不是
that decision is made by the woman rather than the man
这一决定是由女人了 而不是人
if you do have children, would you want them educated
如果你有孩子， 你会希望他们的教育
in the way that you've been educated?
在你被教育的方式吗？
I don't know how things have changed
我不知道事情是如何发生改变
but basically you've still got this emphasis on just getting through exams
但基本上你还有这个 在刚刚通过考试的重点
you know, which isn't really education
你知道，这不是真正的教育
cause most of the stuff you come out of school with is absolutely useless
因为大部分的东西，你来 从学校是无用的
you don't need it
你不需要它
So how would you bring them up?  Educate them?
那你怎么带 他们吗？教育他们？
well I don't know, I suppose the easy answer is..
我不知道， 我想答案很简单..
teach them more relevant things
教他们更多有关的东西
get them to think for themselves
让他们自己思考
a bit more, which schools don't do enough
一点，学校 没有足够的
Would you contemplate putting them into the private sector of education?
你会考虑把它们 为民办教育部门？
no.. no
没有。没有
definitely not
绝对不是
Why?
为什么呢？
well it's just the principle, that's all there is to it.
这只是原则， 这就是全部。
What is the principle?
原理是什么？
well, the principle is that the private schools help
好的，其原理是 私立学校的帮助
to keep the old class system going
让老班制
they're part of it, they perpetuate it
他们是它的一部分，他们延续它
so I'm certainly not going to be involved in that
所以我当然不是 要在那
when I came through school at the end, perhaps of the..
当我来到学校 最后，也许..
well, lets say the ideals of the 60's were still there
好的，让我们说理想 60年代还在那里
even though it was the 70's
即使是70的
and, that one was always led to believe
而且，一个总是LED相信
that there were golden opportunities
有金色的机会
but of course there aren't
当然没有
and very much now, people of my generation are beginning to realize
和现在很多，我的人 代开始意识到
what perhaps sixteen-year-olds know, now at sixteen
也许十六岁 现在知道，在十六
I'm only just beginning to see that now at 27
我才刚开始 看，现在是27
that in fact, you know, there aren't..
事实上，你知道，有人就不行。
there's no such thing as sort of, mobility, in any sense of the word
有没有这样的东西作为一种， 流动性，在任何意义上的字
you know, it's very difficult to move up
你知道，这将是非常困难的
do you think you've had as fair opportunity as other people? - oh god no
你认为你是公平的 机会是其他人？-噢上帝没有
In what way?
在哪一方面？
a lot of people have got it made for them still, haven't they?
很多人已经 他们还，不是吗？
they've got it all lined up
他们都排队
how?
怎么用？
well..
好的。
like the public school..
像公立学校。
I don't want to slag off people who are in the program with m
我不想离开的人渣 是谁在M程序
not slag them off personally
没有他们个人渣
but I mean, they had it set up for them, didn't they?
但我的意思是，他们已经建立了 对他们来说，不是吗？
it's a big problem, it caused a lot of discussion I think
这是一个很大的问题，它引起的 很多的讨论，我认为
the workers do tend to take a few liberties as regards to strikes
工人们往往需要几 关于罢工的自由
I would like to think that democracy is here to stay
我想， 民主在这里停留
perhaps we haven't got a full democracy, in fact, we problably haven't
也许我们没有充分的民主， 事实上，我们的因素，没有
it's a..
这是A。
it's a pretty good system
这是一个很好的系统
are you surprised by the way England is being governed?
你吃惊的样子 英国是被统治的？
I'm not surprised with the people who govern us at the moment, no
我不感到惊讶的人 谁统治我们的那一刻，没有
- Why? - I've even stopped being amazed
为什么呢？ 我甚至不再惊讶
well..
好的。
I don't want to get dragged into party politics, you know
我不想牵扯到方 政治，你知道的
but basically it's the most..
但基本上它是最的。
incompetent, uncaring, bloody.. we've ever had
无能的，不关心， 血腥的。我们曾经有过的
Well if I can't be an astronaut, I'd like to be
如果我不能成为一名宇航员， 我想成为
a Bradwell sergeant in the police force, like my dad is
在一个布拉德韦尔中士 警察，像我爸爸
Do you want to be rich?
你想发财？
I wouldn't mind
我不介意
I think once I can get myself going
我想一旦我能自己走
I can work solid, yeah
我可以工作扎实，是的
but it's the motive
但它的动机
which is very hard to acquire
这是很难获得
yeah..
是的。
I'm dead lazy
我死了懒惰
- yeah.. - And how did you deal with it?
-是的。 -你是如何处理的？
not much
不多
I'm just hard to get.. you know I'm not the sort of person who can get
我只是很难得到的。你知道我不是 的人谁可以排序得到
charged up very quickly
带电的很快
I am really lazy, you know
我真的很懒，你知道的
if I've got things to do I'd sooner make a cup of tea first and read the paper
如果我有事情要做我宁愿做 一杯茶一读报纸
he always looks on the negative side of life before he looks on the positive
他看起来总是在消极的一面 在他看来在积极的生活
whereas perhaps I'm the opposite
而我也许相反
and that in a sense is an area of conflict, yes
这在某种意义上 是一个冲突的领域，是的
yeah, a clash of personalities
是的，个性的冲突
- yeah - And how did you deal with that?
是啊 -你怎么处理呢？
well, as you deal with all people like that, you just give them a good..
嗯，当你处理所有的人 这样，你就给他们一个好的..
kick and say, you know..
踢和说，你知道的。
"wake up to it" you know, that kind of thing
“醒醒吧” 你知道，那种事
and do you see any areas of conflict in the future for you?
你看到任何地方 你在未来的冲突？
In personality?
在人格？
no.. no I don't not really
没有。没有我不 不完全是
because I think we both appreciate each other's personalities,
因为我想我们都欣赏 对方的性格，
in fact, it would be quite dull to be exactly the same
事实上，这将是相当 是完全一样的无聊
I mean, there is something quite
我的意思是，有一些相当
exciting in being different
令人兴奋的是不同的
in that it isn't as predictable
因为它不可预测的
you know, we're not along the same track all the time
你知道，我们不走 同一轨道上的所有时间
on the grass..
在草。
- we play international wrestling - yeah
我们玩国际摔跤 是啊
that's only in summertime though
只有在夏季虽然
What have been for you the best times?
什么是最适合你的时间？
Tommy Smith scoring the second goal in Rome
汤米史密斯评分 在罗马的第二个目标
definitely.. one of the all-times
绝对的。其中的所有时间
Which game was that?
这是什么游戏？
"Which game was that?"
“这是什么游戏？”
that was the European Cup final, 1977
这是欧洲冠军杯决赛，1977
you know, after that it was all.. nothing else compares with it really
你知道的，之后是所有的。 没有什么比真的
so, it's hard to think of anything else
所以，去想事情很难
oh, I'll tell you what was another good moment, I was um...
哦，我会告诉你什么是另一个 好的时刻，我嗯…
a group I played in..
一组我了..
were doing quite well... a few occasions, that was good
都做得很好… 有几次，这很好
Tell me about that.
告诉我。
It's just a local band, I was in till fairly recently
这只是一个当地的乐队， 我是直到最近
you know, just played pubs and that, but it was very enjoyable
你知道的，只是起到了酒吧， 但这是非常愉快的
You know, when you get a good reaction from people
你知道，当你得到的 从人的良好反应
it's just one of the best things you can have really
这是一个最好的 你真的会有
Do you ever get that in your work?
你有你的工作吗？
no, god no.
不，神号
Why?
为什么呢？
well, what are you asking?
好的，你有什么要求？
If they applaud at the end of each lesson or something?
如果他们鼓掌 每节课结束吗？
No, just that excitement, that communication?
不，只是兴奋， 沟通？
no.. no I don't
没有。没有我不
Do you think people change much?
你认为人们改变多少？
Or, do you think we saw
或者，你认为我们看到的
you, the man as a 7 year old boy?
你的人， 作为一个7岁的男孩吗？
I thought for awhile that was a bit too simple, but I think it's true
一会儿，我认为这是一个 太简单了，但我认为它是真实的
because after that your barriers begin to go up
因为在那 你的障碍开始了
you learn how to fend off things like I was just saying
你如何抵挡的东西 像我刚才说的
obviously when 7 seven you don't think about it, you just come out with it
显然，当你不想7七 关于它，你就说出来
so yeah, to a point you reflect that
所以啊，你一点 反映
So the boy at 7, is in a sense, the real you?
所以在7岁的男孩， 在某种意义上，真正的你吗？
Yeah, it's sort of..
是的，这是种..
the essential.. the essential Peter Davies
所必不可少的。 彼得戴维斯的本质
There were nine other children filmed in 1963.
还有其他九个孩子拍摄 1963。
What of them?
什么样的人？
If we did all um, love Geoffery, and we all want to marry him -Yeah
如果我们做了所有UM，爱的杰弗里， 我们都想嫁给他-是的
I think I know the one that he'd likes.. best..
我想我知道就是他 喜欢。最好的..
and that's her
这是她
and I wasn't talking today and Brown sent me out for nothing
我说的不是今天 布朗派我没有
I feel like rumbling when there' already been a fight
我觉得当有隆隆 已经打了一仗
If I can't be an astronaut, I think I'll be a coach driver.
如果我不能成为一名宇航员， 我想我会成为一个教练司机。
I read the Financial Times
我读了金融时报
What's happened to these children?
什么是这些孩子的事吗？
Where are they and what are they doing?
他们，他们在做什么呢？
We'll see tomorrow night.
我们会看到明天晚上。
If someone comes up and starts fighting then.. I think it serves them right
如果有人来了，开始战斗 然后。我认为这是对的
I know the one he likes.. best.. and it's her!
我知道一个他喜欢的。最好的.. 这是她的！
I think it's not a bad idea to pay for school
我认为这不是个坏主意 支付学校
I'm going to work in Woolworth's
我打算在伍尔沃思的工作
I'd just walk around, and see what I can find
我只是走走， 看看我能找到什么
I think I'll be a coach driver
我想我会成为一个教练司机
I don't like um..
我不喜欢..
the big boys..
大男孩..
hitting us and..
打和。
and a prefect sending us out.. out for nothing
和一个完美的发送 我们出去了。了没有
I know I prefer to be alone really.
我知道，我喜欢一个人真的。
when I said that
当我说
I know.. I know even now, I meant that
我知道..我知道 即使是现在，我的意思是
if someone dropped me out in the Sahara desert
如果有人把我了 在撒哈拉沙漠
I probably would have been happy more or less, if you get the point
我可能会很高兴 更多或更少，如果你明白这一点
say you had a wife
说你有个妻子
say, say, say..
说，说，说。
say you had to eat what they cooked you and..
说你吃 他们给你做的。
and say I don't like greens, well I don't.
说我不喜欢绿色， 我可不行。
and say, she said
说，她说
"you have to eat, what you get"
“你吃，你得到了什么”
well I don't like greens.. so she gives me greens.. and it..
我不喜欢绿色的。 所以她给我绿色的。和..
and that's it..
这是它。
I find it hard to express emotion most of the time
我发现很难表达 情感的大部分时间
though I'm getting on top of that
虽然我在那
more now, you know?
现在，你知道吗？
Just the simple things to say to Susan, I love you, something like that
只是简单的事情说给苏珊， 我爱你，像那样的东西
I mean, I can tell you about it, but
我的意思是，我可以告诉你，但是
I really haven't been able to say it freely
我真的没有 说它自由
to Sue, you know?
苏，你知道吗？
Has he proposed to you?
他向你求婚了吗？
yeah, it was strange, we went off and bought the engagement ring first
是的，奇怪的是，我们去了 第一次买了订婚戒指
and then I said to him, you haven't really proposed to me yet -tongue tied
然后我对他说，你没有 真的向我求婚但张口结舌
as you can gather, he's sort of very shy
你可以收集， 他很腼腆
What was it that you fell in love with? What is it about him?
是什么使你爱上了吗？ 这是关于什么的呢？
his helplessness, I suppose
他的无助，我想
there's the motherly instinct in me
这就是我的母性本能
to pick him up, and cuddle him..
去接他，拥抱他。
he's also very good looking, I think, but he doesn't agree with me
他也很好看，我想， 但他不同意我的看法
and in the summer, he's got this cute little bum in shorts
在夏天， 他穿着短裤了这个可爱的小屁股
Paul and Susan live in Melbourne, Australia
保罗和苏珊住在 墨尔本澳大利亚
Four years ago they sold everything they had
四年前他们出售的一切 他们
bought an old Bedford van, and went on a trip through Central and Western Australia
买了一个旧的贝德福德范， 和去旅行通过中央 和澳大利亚西部
it took 7 months, and they travelled 15,000 miles
它花了7个月， 他们走了15000英里
I think it brought us closer together
我认为它给我们带来了更紧密的联系在一起
because we really got to know each other and relied on each other so much
因为我们真的彼此了解了 并依靠对方这么多
I'd never been so relaxed in my life, I felt a lot more confident in myself
我从来没有在我的生活如此轻松， 我觉得自己更自信
just great fun really
只是非常有趣，真的
no pressures or worries, everything was forgotten
没有压力或烦恼， 一切都忘记了
when we got to Perth,' I was ready to fly home
当我们到达珀斯时，” 我正准备飞回家
being together so much, it was hard
在一起这么多，很难
but then we settled down and must have settled down really well because
然后我们坐下来要 安定下来，真的很好，因为
I got pregnant and everything so something must have been going right
我怀孕了，所以 一定是发生了什么事情吗
I think it's, now, why people like to get back to nature and like to feel that
我认为，现在，人们为什么喜欢 回到自然，喜欢这种感觉
that they aren't living in the 20th Century..
他们不 生活在第二十世纪。
to me, it's just like an old dream that you wish could come true, you know
对我来说，这就像一个古老的梦想， 你的愿望能够成真，你知道的
living next to nature, like pioneers type of thing
生活在自然， 喜欢的东西的先锋型
I love the place, you know
我喜欢的地方，你知道的
I find it hard to put into words really, what it is
我发现很难把文字，真的， 这是什么
you've got the country
你已经得到了国家
you've got bush, the outback
你已经得到了布什，内陆
you can do more or less anything you want, I think, here
你可以做的更多或更少的东西 你想，我想，在这里
whether you can do that in England, I don't know
你是否能做到 在英格兰，我不知道
I think this is the part we enjoyed the most
我认为这是一部分 我们最喜欢的
because we really went out in the middle of nowhere
因为我们真的去了 在没人的地方
where we had to carry our own petrol and our own water
我们必须把我们自己的 汽油和我们自己的水
to do us for the 3 or 4 days we were out that way
我们为3或4 天我们都这样
while we were up in Carnarvon, we went and stayed on a sheep station
当我们在卡那封， 我们去住在一个绵羊牧场
up there with our friend from Melbourne, Bruce
还有我们的朋友 来自墨尔本，布鲁斯
and It was about a million acres, just under a million acres, the sheep station
这是约一百万亩，只是 在一百万亩，羊站
Bruce from the Yanrey Station, he got ahold of sometails from the roo-shredder
布鲁斯从扬里站，他得到了 到sometails从袋鼠碎纸机
so we could try kangaroo tail stew
所以我们可以尝试的袋鼠尾巴炖肉
yeah, it was a bit rough
是的，这是一个有点粗糙
we had nothing to throw it in. - a bit sinewy
我们没有把它。 一位强壮的
It gave us our own peace of mind that we could settle down
它给了我们内心的宁静 我们能安定下来
and now have a family, that we had done something, we hadn't just been nobodys
现在有一个家庭，我们所做的 我们没有的东西，只是没人
and lived in suburbia all our lives
住在郊区的所有我们的生活
we'd done something that we were proud of that..
我们得做点什么 我们该感到自豪。
you know, we'd accomplished on our own
你知道，我们会 在我们自己的成就
Do you want this for the children?
你想要孩子吗？
I'd love it for the children
我爱这孩子
I was once taught when I was at school that
我曾经教过的 我是在学校
travel could be the best education and
旅行是最好的教育
living in conditions where you have to fend for yourself
生活在有条件的地方，你 要照顾自己
and you have to use your own initiative is very good and
你必须使用你的 主动性是很好的，
I would like it
我想它
I was gonna be a policeman but I thought how hard it would be to join in
我想是一个警察，但是我 思想如何努力，它会加入
I just haven't made up my mind yet, I was gonna be a phys-ed teacher but
我还没有拿定主意， 我会是一个体育老师但
one of the teachers told me that you had to get up into university
一位老师告诉我， 你已经获得了进入大学
At 21, Paul was working as a junior partner
在21，保罗是一名初中 合作伙伴
for a firm of bricklayers in Melbourne
对于一个公司的瓦工 在墨尔本
I'm not great at bricklaying, right
我不擅长瓦工，右
but if I wasn't good enough and my boss didn't think I was good enough
但是如果我不足够好，我的老板 不认为我已经足够好了
he would have never made me a junior partner
他从来没有让我 一个小伙伴
I went out on my own as a subcontracter
我去了我自己 作为分包队伍
not long after the last show
最后一场演出后不久
then I started with a partner, I organized everything
然后我开始与一个合作伙伴， 我安排好一切
I bought all the equipment because I didn't want to
我买了所有的设备 因为我不想
be dependent on someone else
依赖别人
things didn't work out between the two of us, he was a bit lazy
事情没有解决之间的 我们两个，他是一个有点懒惰
Do you have the right temperament, do you think? To run your own business?
你有正确的气质， 看到了吗？运行你自己的生意？
if you're talking about employing other people, I'm not hard enough
如果你在谈论使用其他 人，我不够硬
I'm a little bit slow with working out things on the job
我有一点慢 工作上的事情工作
not in particular the laying of the bricks but
没有特别 但铺设砖
but I am a fairly slow thinker when you've got to work something out
但我是一个相当缓慢的思想家的时候 你得做点什么
I think it'll end up being my job for life, probably
我想这会是我的 工作生活，可能
not that I want it that way
我不想就这样
cause it gets harder as you get older, I think
因为它会更难 当你老了，我想
I've got twenty three..  pieces..
我有二零三。件。
and I don't know how many..
我不知道很多。
how many.. pieces I've got now
多少..我现在有件
26 past 10 with Doug... 15 degrees in Melbourne... at the moment...
26过去10道格…15度 在墨尔本…目前……
They live in a working class suburb of Melbourne.
他们生活在一个工作 墨尔本郊区的类。
Paul earns
保罗收入
owns two cars
拥有两辆车
and bought his hours for
买了他的时间
we're Mr. and Mrs. average, that's just true
我们平均先生和夫人， 这是真的
we probably earn an average income
我们可能获得的平均收入
just an average family
只是一个普通的家庭
a good fist away by Russo up towards center wing... Robertson this time...
成功了日俄朝 中央翼…罗伯森这一次…
Susan works part time as a hair dresser
苏珊的作品的一部分时间是理发师
and they have two children,
他们有两个孩子，
Katie and Robert.
凯蒂和罗伯特。
Are you ambitious for your children Paul?
你有野心 你的孩子的保罗？
I said something one morning, that one day Robert would be a brain surgeon
我说有一天早晨，一个 一天罗伯特会成为脑外科医生
that was a joke, I mean like if he was a brain surgeon, all good and well but
这是一个笑话，我的意思是，如果他是 脑外科医生，不错但
but it would be nice to let them go one step up from us, I think
但它会让好 他们走上一步我们，我认为
put it this way, I hope he is better at school work than I was
用这种方式，我希望他 在学校的工作比我更好
so, that he's got a choice
所以，他有一个选择
you know, because really..
你知道的，因为真的..
the education standard that I got, I didn't have a choice
教育标准 我得到了，我没有选择
what does university mean?
大学是什么意思？
Paul started his school life at a children's home near London.
保罗在开始他的学校生活 孩子们的家附近的伦敦。
When he was eight he emigrated to Australia with his father.
他八岁时移居 澳大利亚与他的父亲。
Were you happy at the children's home in England?
你的快乐 在英国儿童之家？
we didn't mind it really because we didn't know what was going on
我们不介意真的因为 我们不知道发生了什么
cause we were a bit young then
因为我们年轻一点，然后
What regrets do you have about your education then?
有什么遗憾你 那么你的教育？
I didn't work hard enough
我还不够努力
I was just very lazy at school
我只是很懒，在学校
you know, if you're lazy and you don't work at school, you suffer for it
你知道，如果你懒，你不 在学校工作，为你受苦
there needs to be a little more discipline
需要有 多学科
if private schools are better..
如果私立学校更好。
you'd be far better off spending your money sending your kids there
你会比现在更好的支出 你的钱送你的孩子有
then getting a video, a new television..
然后得到一个视频，一个新的电视台。
or something like that, I think
或类似的东西，我想
What else do you want for your kids, that you didn't have?
你还想为你的孩子什么， 你没有？
a happier family life, I think
一个快乐的家庭生活，我认为
don't take me wrong, it wasn't miserable
不要误会我的意思，这不是痛苦
I think it could have been better
我认为这可能是更好的
I think that'd be one of the most important things
我想那是其中的一个 最重要的事情
well my mother and father got, well they separated originally, I think
我的母亲和父亲了，好的 他们分离的最初，我想
and..
和..
eventually got divorced
最终离婚了
I went to the boarding school for one year and then we emigrated to Australia
我去了寄宿学校之一 年，然后我们移居澳大利亚
my father got remarried
我的父亲再婚了
And how do you get on with your stepmother?
你怎么得到 你的继母？
pretty well, but like I said before
很好，但是就像我之前说的
I'm not.. just not close.. I'm not really close to my father either
我不是..不关。 我不是真的很接近我的父亲
Do you have any regrets about about the fact that
你有任何的遗憾 关于这个事实
that you weren't closer to him when you were younger?
你不是接近 他年轻时？
yeah, I suppose... in a way I suppose
是的，我想…一方面我想
he was always there, you know, I could always
他总是在那儿，你知道的， 我可以永远
talk to him but it was different we were sort of..
跟他说话，但它是不同的 我们有点..
we were, sort of, distant friends I mean, we always got on fairly well
我们，是的，遥远的朋友 我的意思是，我们总是很好
we didn't see much of each other
我们不常见面
- here's grandad.. here's grandad.. - hey!
-这是爷爷的。这是爷爷的。 -嘿！
he said actually, to his wife Barbara that..
他说，实际上， 他的妻子巴巴拉..
that he missed out on his own children
他错过了 在他自己的孩子
andthat he's not going to miss out on these
而他不是 要错过这些
divorce was something new to me until I grew up and was
离婚是新的东西给我 直到我长大了
knew what the meaning of it all really was
知道什么 它所有的意义真的是
there were no divorces in my family
在我的家庭里有没有离婚
I think of what Paul has been through, I mean
我想什么保罗 已通过，我的意思是
Paul doesn't say that it was very bad but I wouldn't want that for my children
保罗不说，这是非常糟糕的 但我不希望我的孩子
it does worry me
它让我担心
you know, because it happens so much these days
你知道，因为它发生 所以这些天
only time will tell what happens
只有时间会告诉你发生了什么
divorcing your wife, what does it get you?
你的妻子离婚， 它给你什么了？
it messes up your own life
它会搅乱你的生活
it messes up the kids life, wife's life
它弄乱了孩子们的生活，妻子的生活
I don't think half the people who get divorced even think about it properly
我不认为有一半的人 离婚甚至认真考虑
What mark has it left on you, the fact that you were brought up
标记有什么留给你的， 事实上，你长大了
within a bad marriage?
在一个糟糕的婚姻？
the only thing I can say, that I think might have come from that is
我唯一能说的，我认为 可能来自：
just my lack of confidence
我缺乏自信
and being able to show my feelings, really, I suppose
能给我 的感觉，真的，我想
he is down on him self, he has this excuse where he says,
他对他自己，他 这个借口，他说在那里，
"I'm only a bricklayer, I don't.. it's got nothing to do with me"
“我只是一个泥瓦匠，我不行。 它与我没有关系”
I don't know why it is, I get really frustrated with him
我不知道为什么它是， 我真的对他失望
I want to ring his neck sometimes when he does it
我想他的颈环 有时当他做它
but, he's getting better
但是，他越来越好
So, do you feel there's any conflict ahead?
所以，你感觉到的 任何冲突吧？
If Sue wants a job and a career?
如果苏希望工作和职业生涯？
what's come up so far, since we've been married, we've handled that
怎么了到目前为止，因为我们 结婚了，我们已经处理了
really, I think, Susan would probably be
真的，我认为，苏珊可能会
the be the best one to start a.. be a businesswoman and I'll stay at home
这是最好的开始了。 是一个商人，我就呆在家里
you know..
你知道..
I have to push him out of the house sometimes,I think needs a bit of extra
我把他从房子里出来 有时，我觉得需要一点额外的
male companionship because he..
男性伴侣因为他..
being a bricklayer, he only works with one fellow
作为一个泥瓦匠， 他只能与一个家伙
he doesen't, we don't have a social life with work type of thing
他没有，我们没有一个社会 随着东西工作式的生活
well he doesn't because it's only just one person as well as himself
他并不因为它的 只有一个人以及自己
and his basketball, I think he really enjoys it
他的篮球， 我觉得他真的很喜欢它
but he doesn't really let on how much he enjoys it
但他并没有真的让 他是多么喜欢它
I suppose you could see me now, when I was seven, in a way
我想你现在能看到我， 我七岁时，在一个方式
like I think it was pretty obvious that I wasn't going to be a doctor
我认为这是很明显的 我不想成为一个医生
You seemed like such a sad little boy.
你像这样一个可怜的小男孩。
but that's me though, ha ha
但那是我，哈哈
I know I was pretty..
我知道我很漂亮。
you know.. long faced sortta thing..
你知道..长期面对sortta的事。
I was like that sometimes out here too, I was always getting knocked about
我是这样的，有时也在这里， 我总是收到了
I don't like greens, well I don't..
我不喜欢绿色，那么我也不行。
the first show I saw, was at 21
第一个展示我所看到的，是在21
when I saw him at seven, I just wanted to cry, he seemed so pathetic
当我在七看到他，我只是想 哭，他似乎很可怜
he..
他..
I suppose, I don't know
我想，我不知道
it's hard to say, it really made me go to jelly inside, you know?
这很难说，真的 让我去果冻里面，你知道吗？
to see him like that
看到他那样
And do you think it's true that we can see the man in the seven year old boy?
你认为这是真的，我们可以 在七岁的男孩看到的那个人吗？
yes, yes it is because in that he was a very gentle and..
是的，这是因为在他 是一个很温柔的。
and um.. not gentle..
嗯..不温柔的。
caring person, yeah he's always..
有爱心的人，是的 他总是..
cared about other people and always been able to work his way
关心别人 和总是能够按照自己的方式
talk his..
他讲的。
try to give an explanation for saying something he really doesn't want to do
试着给说一个解释 他真的不想做
you know like, "what if I"
你知道，“如果我”
"didn't like to eat my greens" and all that sort of thing, I mean
“不喜欢吃我的菜” 以及诸如此类的事情，我的意思是
he always still does that, the "what if", you know "what if"
他还总是这样的， “如果”，你知道“如果”
and you know he doesn't really want to do that
你知道他不 真的想这样做
so he's trying to talk himself out of it
所以他想 自己说出来
yeah.. yeah..
是的。是的。
Does he eat greens now? - he loves them
他吃蔬菜吗？ 他爱他们
he loves them, he loves them
他爱他们，他爱他们
What do you remember of England?
你还记得英国吗？
well it seemed to be raining all of the time, I wouldn't
这似乎是好的 时间，我不会
stake my life on it but..
以我的生命在它但..
-we've got a lot more than we would have in England
-我们已经有了很多比 我们会在英国
from what other people tell us
从其他什么人告诉我们
but there again..
但有一次..
when it comes to work I don't
工作的时候我不
sit down on my backside, I'll go and chase it
坐在我的背后， 我要去追它
so it's hard to say
所以很难说
but I'd say, like in general, that.. but I've probably..
但我想说的，像在一般， 那。但我可能..
I've probably done better here than I would have there
我可能做的更好 这里比我都有
the family is going to come first, but I'm still
这家要 第一，但我还是
I'm still going to be working and we'll progress..
我仍然会工作 我们会进步。
you know.. - I'd love for Paul to build me a house
你知道.. 我对保罗的爱给我建一个房子
and I know he'd be happy once he'd done it
我知道他 快乐，一旦他做到了
but he's got his children and then to build his own home...
但他有自己的孩子，然后 建立自己的家…
it really would be the icing on the cake for both of us
它真的会结冰 我们两个蛋糕
I read The Financial Times
我读了金融时报
I read The Observer and The Times
我读了观测器和时代
what do you like about it?
你喜欢它的哪一点？
well, I like.. I usually look at the headlines and then read about them..
好的，我喜欢。我通常看 标题然后读他们。
about it
关于它的
I like my newspaper because I've got shares in it..
我喜欢我的报纸，因为我已经有了 股票在它。
and I know everyday what the shares are - The stuff that misers like you like!
我知道每天多少股份 -你喜欢的东西，守财奴！
but on Monday's they don't move up so I don't look at it
但在星期一的他们不 上移动，我不看它
what's the point of the program?
该计划的重点是什么？
the point of the program is to reach a comparison
该计划的重点是 达到一个比较
I don't think it is..
我不认为它是。
because we're not necessarily typical examples
因为我们不一定 典型的例子
I think that's what people who've seen the program might think - yes, falsely
我想这就是人所看到的 该程序可能会认为-是的，虚伪的
- I mean.. - they tend to typecast us
我的意思是.. 他们往往是我们
so everything we say, they'll think
所以我们说，他们会认为
"oh, that's a typical result of the public school system" - yes
“哦，这是一个典型的结果 公立学校系统”-是的
Well, do you think there is any truth behind the ideas behind the program?
嗯，你觉得有任何真相 在程序背后的想法？
That certain people have more options than others?
某些人 比别人更多的选项？
it's certainly true that more people.. more people know they have
这当然是真的，更多的人。 更多的人知道他们
more options or imagine they have
更多的选项或想象他们
I think in practical terms..
我想在现实中的。
the difference in the numerical number of options isn't that great
在数值的差异 伟大的选择不是数
but the mere knowledge creates an option in itself - exactly, yes
但单纯的知识创造 期权本身没错，是的
so I think we do have more options
所以我认为我们有更多的选择
and it is undesirable but it's very difficult to correct
这是不可取的是 很难改正
I don't think it is undesirable! at all!
我简直难以相信 不良的！完全。
I think what is undesirable is people who have had options
我认为是不受欢迎的人 谁有选项
don't make advantage of them.. take best advantage of them
不要利用他们。 充分利用他们
when I leave this school I'm going to College Court
当我离开这所学校 我要上大学法院
then I would be going to Westminster Boarding School if I pass the exam
然后我会去威斯敏斯特 寄宿学校，如果我通过考试
and then we think I'm going to
然后我们 想我
Cambridge and Trinity Hall
剑桥 圣三一堂
John went to Westminster school
约翰去了 威斯敏斯特学校
and at twenty-one was in his final year reading law at Christ Church Oxford
在二十一是在他最后的 在牛津基督教堂年阅读法
I do believe that parents have a right to educate children as they think fit
我相信父母有权利 教育孩子按照他们认为合适的
and I think someone who works
我认为工作的人
on an assembly line in some of these car factories
在一些装配线 这些汽车工厂
and earning a huge wage could well afford to send their children to
获得巨大的工资能 买得起送他们的孩子去
a private school
私立学校
just because..
只是因为..
just because some sorts of people don't put that as high on their priorities as
只是因为某些人不 把高优先级为
you know, have a smart car or something
你知道，有一个聪明的汽车或什么的
I'm going to Charter House
我要去租房子
and after that Trinity Hall, Cambridge
这圣三一堂后，剑桥
Andrew went to Charter House and read law at Trinity Hall, Cambridge
安得烈去租房子 圣三一堂读法律，剑桥
and you can never be sure of leaving your children
你永远不能确定 让你的孩子
any worldly goods
任何世俗的货物
but at least you can be sure once you've given them a good education
但至少可以肯定的 一旦你给他们一个好的教育
that's something that no one can take away
这东西 没有人能带走
when I leave school, I'm going to the Dragon School
当我离开学校， 我要去龙学校
I might.. and mummy is.. and I might go to..
或许我..妈妈是.. 我会去的。
after, I might go to Charter House, Marlborough
之后，我可能会去 租房子，马尔伯勒
and..
和..
I can't.. I can't remember all the other places
我不会。我想不起来了 所有其他的地方
because mummy has got so many places... but these're some of them
因为妈妈有很多 的地方…但这些是他们中的一些人
What about university Charles?
关于大学的查尔斯？
I might go to Oxford
我可能会去牛津
Charles went to Marlborough but didn't make it to Oxford.
查尔斯去马尔伯勒却 没去牛津。
Instead, he went to Durham University.
相反，他去了杜伦大学。
I'd say, I'm pleased I didn't because it's very much a sort of..
我想说，我很高兴我没有 因为它非常多的一种了。
sort of Marlborough..
马尔堡..排序
prep school..
预备学校。
Marlborough-Oxbridge conveyor belt
马尔堡牛津剑桥输送带
and you get shoved out at the end..
和你挤到了在结束。
and you..
和你..
when you go to Oxbridge
当你去牛津大学
and obviously it's not true in all cases but
显然，这不是真的 在所有的情况下，但
I think for the majority
我认为对大多数
they mix with the same as they were with a school
他们和他们一样 是一所学校
When they were 21, we asked them what they thought they would be doing at 28.
在他们21岁的时候，我们问他们什么 他们认为他们将做在28。
John
约翰
I might be at the bar
我可能会在酒吧
Doing what?
做什么？
perhaps chancellory practice
也许大臣实践
How do you see your life at 28?
你怎么看28你的生活？
What do you want for your self then?
你要为你的自我呢？
I'd quite like to be married by then
我很想再结婚
John has just announced his engagement.
约翰刚刚宣布订婚。
He is a successful barrister in the chancellory division of the high court.
他是一个成功的律师 高等法院的大臣分。
At 21 these were his thoughts about his career.
21这是他的 他的职业生涯的想法。
law sort of interests me
我感兴趣的法律类
I think it's sort of..
我认为这是..
a good life
一个好的生活
it's..
它的。
it's hard work but you sort of
这是一项艰苦的工作 但是你什么
when you get to a certain..
当你到一个特定的。
eminence, you know you take the work you want and
阁下，你知道你 把你想要的工作
you take the holidays you want
你把你想要的假期
you don't really dance to anyone's tune
你不跳舞的人的曲调
all of which quite suits me
所有这一切都很适合我
And what about Charles?
那查尔斯怎么办？
hard to say..
很难说..
probably scribbling away in some basement
可能的涂鸦 在一些地下室
for a some London newspaper or something
对于一些伦敦 报纸之类的东西
Charles did scribble away for an East London newspaper.
查尔斯也写了 在东伦敦的报纸。
He moved on after a year
他在一年后
and joined the BBC where he now works as and assistant producer.
加入英国广播公司他现在在哪里 作为和助理制片人。
And Andrew, what did he want?
安得烈，他想做什么？
I'd like to be a solicitor and also fairly successful
我想成为一个律师 也相当成功
Andrew is a solicitor working for a large firm in the city.
安得烈是一个律师的工作 在城里的一家大型公司。
What qualities do you think it needs to be successful?
哪些品质在你认为 它需要的是成功的吗？
well you have to have a legal ability in my business, obviously
你有一个法律 在我的业务能力，明显
and you have to have a 'bedside manner' as far as clients are concerned
你必须有一个“态度” 只要客户所关心的
cause it's no good being brilliant if you can't communicate with your clients
因为它是没有好处的辉煌如果 你不能和你的客户沟通
What do you think about girlfriends at your age?
你的意思如何 在你这个年龄，关于女朋友的？
I've got one but I don't think much of her
我有一只 我不太喜欢她
The girls never.. never
女孩子永远不会的。绝不
never do what the boys want them to
不要做男孩们想要的
they always start playing with dolls
他们总是开始玩娃娃
when the boys want to play rough and tumble
当孩子们想要的 打混战
it's quite true
这是真的
I don't think I financially come from the same background
我不认为我的财务 来自相同的背景
Andrew didn't for a 'Haughty Deb' he went for a good 'Yorkshire Lass'
安得烈没有一个“傲慢的” 他去了一个很好的“约克郡小女孩”
which I mean, obviously he knew what he wanted
我的意思是，很明显他 知道自己想要什么
Andrew and Jane were married 18 months ago.
安得烈和简 18个月前结婚了。
I think I'm pretty down to Earth and I
我想我脚踏实地和我
tend to be less extravagant then maybe some women are
往往是不太奢侈的 也许有些女人
when I go out, I don't buy lots of expensive dresses, I just buy one or two
当我出去的时候，我不买很多 昂贵的衣服，我就买一个或两个
and I even let her pay for them
我甚至让她付出代价
They spend their weekends in the Sussex countryside
他们度过他们的周末 在苏塞克斯乡村
where they are converting an old barn
他们把一个旧谷仓
which they bought with financial help from their parents.
他们买了 从父母的资助。
They plan to live in it permanently when they start a family
他们打算住它 当他们开始一个家庭永久
During a week they have a flat in London
在一个星期他们在伦敦的一个单位
and Jane has a full-time job as a secretary.
简有一个 专职秘书工作。
I think it's not a bad idea to pay for schools
我认为这不是一个坏的 的想法来支付学校
because if we didn't schools would be so nasty and crowded
因为如果我们没有学校 会这么肮脏、拥挤的
- yes - so do I think so?
-是的 所以我这样想？
- yes - and the people in the school's wouldn't
-是的-和人 在学校的不
- the poor people would come rushing in
――可怜的人 会冲进来
- the man in charge of the school would get very angry
负责的人 这所学校就很生气
because he wouldn't be able to pay all of the masters
因为他不可能 支付所有的大师
if he didn't get any money
如果他没有得到任何钱
well, I never really experienced the state system but I think you get
嗯，我从来没有经历过 国家制度，但我认为你的
a better level of education if you can go to a private school
一个更好的教育水平，如果 你可以去私立学校
Do you think it's bad that people like you, opt out of the school system?
你认为坏的人 像你一样，选择了学校的系统？
well, there are really two counter arguments
嗯，真的有 两个计数器参数
first of all, there's the argument that people should have a choice
首先，还有的论点 人应该有一个选择
if they've earned the money to spend it
如果他们挣的钱花掉它
and there's the other argument that if we all went to the same sort of schools
还有，如果其他的论点 我们都去学校一样
those school would probably be better because those people who had influence
这些学校可能会更好 因为那些影响
would do their upmost to make sure they were better
他们会做的最好 确保他们是更好的
if they had to send their children there
如果他们把他们的孩子
whereas they just look back
而他们只要回头
and don't particularly care what happens in the state system
不要在意 在国家制度发生了什么
And what do you feel about that?
你觉得怎么样？
well..
好的。
well, I think probably the latter choice is fairly impractical
嗯，我想可能是后者的选择 是相当不切实际
so, I suppose that one has to continue with the idea of everyone
所以，我认为必须继续 每个人的想法
having a choice
有一个选择
once I had a talk to Grevil, he was in my house
有一次我跟grevil， 他是在我的房子
and
和
I asked Sir if he could put him out of my house
我问他是否能把先生 他离开我的房子
because he was always getting minuses
因为他总是缺点
looking back at our film and us at seven
回顾我们的电影和我们在七
certainly I was a fairly precocious little brat
当然，我是一个相当 早熟的小鬼
and I hope I am no longer
我希望我不再
Do you still read The Financial Times? - no
你还读了金融时报？ -不
you mustn't! no feeding it says!
你不能！不喂它说！
stop it at once!
马上停止！
- I don't think much of the accents - neither do I
我不想太多的口音 -我不知道
- but it doesn't prevent me liking them
但这并不妨碍我喜欢他们
that mustn't be late there, quite quietly...
，不能迟到有， 悄悄……
well yes I do feel I've had the best of everything
是的我真的觉得我 有最好的东西
as far as education is concerned
就教育而言
but, you know, to get here I had to work very hard
但是，你知道，得到 在这里我不得不非常努力地工作
But you don't deny you've had a 'silver spoon'?
但你不能否认 你有一个银勺子？
I think anyone who goes to really good school has had a leg-up
我认为任何人都真的 好的学校有一腿
but I mean, I wouldn't say I'd had been
但我的意思是，我不会说 我会一直
unduly privileged if I'd
如果我过分的特权
missed
错过
exams at my school and had to go to a sort of grotty..
在我的学校和考试 去一个难看的。
grotty public school I wouldn't have thought I'd have had any advantage at all
糟糕的公共学校 我没想到 我会在有任何优势
yes I much say, all this talk about opportunities it's something I did
我得说，这一切都谈 的机会，这是我做的
did slightly object to in the program
的确有点对象 在程序中
we were shown at the age of seven outliningsort of, the academics
我们在七岁进行显示 outliningsort，学者
of a career that most of us.. did in fact pursue, you know
的职业生涯，我们大多数人的。 实际上所追求的，你知道的
you know, each sentence ended up
你知道，每个句子结束了
"John is at Westminster" "Andrew is at Charter House" and everything
“约翰是在威斯敏斯特”安得烈 在租船屋”和所有的一切
it implied that we merely sailed through
它暗示我们仅仅通过
merely manifesting an intention that we had at the age of seven
仅仅体现意图 我们已经七岁了
it didn't show the sleepless nights, the sort of pouring over our books
它并没有显示的不眠之夜， 那种涌入我们的书
you know, all of the sweet and toil that got us to universities
你知道，所有的血汗 让我们去学校
it was presented as if it was just part of some indestructible birth rite
它是作为如果它只是部分 有些坚不可摧的出生礼
and I thought that it was unfair
我认为这是不公平的
that it didn't show having to do beastly jobs on the holidays, you know
它并没有显示出有 在假期的野兽般的工作，你知道的
to make ends meet and things
糊口和事情
it didn't give a very real..
它没有给一个非常真实的。
impression
印象
Do you want to be rich?
你想发财？
yes, because I don't want to be tied down to the dourness of an everyday job
是的，因为我不想被束缚 下一个的日常工作，严厉的
I want to have enough money so that I can indulge in
我希望有足够的钱 这样我可以纵情
the things that might interest me like collecting paintings
使我感兴趣的东西 喜欢收集绘画
I do believe in an ordered and structured society
我相信一个 有序结构的社会
you know
你知道的
we are not exactly alive for very long and we've each got our
我们不是活很长时间 我们每人都有自己
our own job to do and our own little position to be in
我们自己的工作 做我们自己的位置是
some people have.. a better time than others, but it..  you know..
有些人..一个更好的时间 比其他人，但它。你知道..
but it doesn't matter that if you sweep the streets
但这不要紧，如果你扫 街上
you're any less valuable than
你有任何的价值小于
than someone who i running a huge corporation
比我的人 经营一家巨型企业
well not everyone can be at the top
也不是每个人都可以在上面
as long as people are happy with what they are doing
只要人是快乐的 他们正在做的
that's, I think, the greatest good that can be
我认为是的，， 最好能
and this is what worries about these new sort of invidious class attitudes
这就是担心这些 类的新类令人反感的态度
the certain sort of subversive elements are introducing
颠覆性的某种 元素的引入
that are based on envy and things
这是基于嫉妒的事情
John declined to be interviewed at 28.
约翰拒绝接受采访，在28。
He felt satisfied with what was said in the previous films
他感到满意，说的是什么 在以前的电影
and had nothing more to add.
有没有更多补充。
the rich children always make fun of poor children
富人的孩子总是 取笑可怜的孩子
yes - yes, they say, "look at that lovely little sissy over there"
是的，是的，他们说，“看看 那可爱的小娘娘腔在那里”
and they throw things at them
他们扔东西的人
I don't particularly want to be rich but I'd like to have enough money
我尤其不想 丰富的但我想有足够的钱
Well, what do you mean by enough?
嗯，你所说的够吗？
or, enough to have a nice house and..
或者，有足够的好房子的。
and be able to send the children to private school if you want to
能给孩子们 如果你想去私立学校
I really don't see how someone's life can be a failure
我真的不明白别人的 生活可以是一个失败的
if I became a journalist and got sacked at 30
如果我成为一名记者 30、被解雇了
it's probably because I'd grown  out of it or I'd changed
这可能是因为我长大了 或者我会改变
so I was no longer suitable, I'd find something else which was
所以我不再是合适的，我会找到的 一些其他的东西是
I'd find that I enjoyed and that my talents were suited to
我发现我喜欢 我的人才适合
Charles has found a career suited to his talents
查尔斯发现了一个职业 适合自己的才华
At the BBC he makes documentary films,
在英国广播公司他使纪录片，
he decided not to take part in this film.
他决定不 参加这部电影。
I'm quite happy living in the society that I am living in
我很高兴生活在社会 我的生活中
it's a shame that more people can't get the opportunities that I've had
遗憾的是，更多的人可以不 让我有机会
I'm not sure how one deals with that
我不知道如何处理，
But you've been lucky haven't you? What about those that haven't been so lucky?
但你已经很幸运，不是吗？干嘛 对于那些没那么幸运吗？
I have been very lucky
我已经很幸运了
we pretend we've got swords
我们假装我们有剑
and
和
we makes the noises of swords fighting
我们使剑战斗的声音
and when someone stabs us we go ahhhhh!
当有人捅我们去ahhhhh！
I think if you're healthy and have good friends
我想，如果你是健康的 有好朋友
you can get on perfectly well
你可以过得很好
but everybody would like to be rich
但每个人都想发财
Neil was brought up in a Liverpool suburb,
尼尔了 在利物浦郊区，
went to comprehensive school
去学校
and dropped out of Aberdeen University after one term
并退出了仔 经过一个学期的大学
at 21 he was working as a casual labourer at a building site in London
21岁的他是个休闲 在伦敦的一个建筑工地的工人
I came to London and I contacted an agency for squatters
我来到了伦敦和我联系 代理的木屋
and they were able to
他们能
give me the address of somebody who was able to
给某人的地址 谁能
help people who were looking for accommodation in the London area
帮助那些正在寻找 在伦敦地区的住宿
and by the process of chasing people around I eventually managed to
在追逐的过程 周围的人，我终于设法
to find this place
找到这个地方
I think in questions of squatting
我认为问题蹲
a bit of humanity is more important than vague
一点人性 更重要的是比模糊的
rules about who can live where
关于谁可以住的地方
But you've kicked against the stability that's..
但你已经踢了 对稳定的。
-I don't think I ever had any stability
我不认为我有任何的稳定性
to be quite honest
老实说
I can't think of any time in my life when I ever did
我想不出任何时间 我生命中做过的
I don't think I've been kicking against anything, I think I've been kicking
我不认为我一直反对 什么，我想我已经踢
in midair the whole of my life
在半空中，我的一生
last three years I've been unemployed
过去的三年里，我已经失业
but traveling quite a bit, mostly in Britain
但旅行相当 一点，大部分是在英国
and abroad once or twice but..
外一次或两次，但..
but not as extensively as I used to do
但不广泛 我用来做
thanks, shall I put the luggage in here? or, do you want it in the back?
谢谢，我把行李 在这里吗？或者，你想让它在后面？
I live off money from social security
我住在离社会保障资金
which does me for my rent and my food
这是我的房租和我的食物
I've been moving about a bit between differnent places, really
我一直在一位移动 不同的地方，真的
I'm a bit unsettled but I'm very shortly moving to live in digs
我有点不安但我很 不久搬到生活在苦难
For the last seven years Neil has been moving around Britain.
在过去的七年里，尼尔 已经在英国。
He spent the summer on a farm in North Wales
他花了整个夏天 在威尔士北部的一个农场
and when we found him he had just arrived
当我们发现 他刚刚到达
in the Western Highlands of Scotland.
在苏格兰西部高地。
Do you think people like who live off the stare are scrounging?
你认为人们喜欢谁 靠盯着乞讨？
-no
-不
if the state didn't give us any money, it would probably just mean crime
如果政府不给我们钱， 它可能只是意味着犯罪
and I'm glad I don't have to steal to keep myself alive
我很高兴我不 有偷让自己活着
I do it simply because I don't want to be without any money
我这样做是因为我 不想没有钱
if the money runs out, well
如果钱用完了，好的
then for a few days, there is nowhere to go to
那几天，有 无处可去
that's all you can do
你所能做的
I simply have to find the warmest shed I can find
我只是要找 我可以找到温暖的小屋
Neil rents whatever kind of home he can find.
尼尔租什么样的 他可以找到家。
the last job I had was cooking in a youth hostel, some cleaning work as well
我上一份工作是在一所烹饪 青年旅舍，以及一些清洁工作
I was the only person in the hostel who could speak French
我在旅馆的唯一的人 谁能说法语
so I did a bit of that
所以我做了一点，
Do you eat everyday?
你每天吃吗？
yes
可以
I'm eating better now then I was at times when I was in Aberdeen
我吃得更好，那么我在 的时候，我在香港仔
those days, sometimes I really was short of food
那些日子，我有时真的 缺少食物
well I'm going to take people to the country
我要去 国家的人民
and sometimes take them to the seaside
有时他们带到海边
and have a big loud speaker in the motor coach
在有一个大的扬声器 运动教练
and tell them whereabouts we are and what we're going to do
告诉他们我们的行踪 我们要做的
and where the road is and all about that
那里的道路是所有关于
there's a lot more to do
还有很多的工作要做
in the mountains than there would be in a suburb or a city centre
在山上比将有 在郊区或城市中心
what I found here, in fact, is you don't talk about the weather
我发现这里，事实上，是你 不要谈论天气
because the weather is all around, everyone know it's been raining
因为天气很全， 每个人都知道在下雨
so you don't talk about the weather that makes good sense to me!
所以你不要谈论天气 很好，给我的感觉！
I'm not the sort of person who can go into a pub
我不是那种人 谁能走到一个酒吧
sit down with a drink and listen to the jukebox and talk a lot of rubbish
喝一杯，坐下来听 自动点唱机，说了很多垃圾
a lot of people find that very relaxing
很多人觉得很放松
but, if I'm going to talk to somebody
但是，如果我要找人谈谈
a, I have to be able to hear myself speaking
一，我可以 听到自己说
and b, I have to talk about something that actually has a meaning
B，我想谈谈 真的有意义
I'm not trying to denigrate the way most people relax
我不想贬低的方式 大多数人放松
but I can't do that, so I'm lost in a noisy pub
但我做不到，所以 我迷失在嘈杂的酒吧
I'll sit in a quite corner of a quite pub
我会坐在一个相当 一个酒吧的角落
and then I'll want to talk about literature or something like that
然后我想谈的 文学或类似的东西
which not everybody.. will want to..
并不是每个人都..要想..
How do people regard you here?
人们是如何看待你在这里吗？
well, I'm still known as an eccentric
嗯，我还被称为 偏心的
as I have been since..
我一直至今。
about the age of sixteen or so
大约十六岁左右
Do days seem long for you?
日子很长吗？
they can do
他们能做的
Do you have any friends anywhere?
你在任何地方有朋友吗？
I have some good friends still in England
我仍然有一些好朋友 在英格兰
I don't think I need to go to university because I'm not going to be a teacher
我认为我不需要去上大学 因为我不想成为一个老师
I went to a comprehensive school
我去学校
I found a much bigger course and I found it hard to settle into at first
我发现了一个更大的课程 我发现很难进入第一
I did make an application to Oxford
我做了一个在牛津的应用
but I didn't get in
但我不会
well I think that's in the past now and that's..
我想说的 在过去和现在，的。
I don't whether I would have been any happier at Oxford
我不知道我会 任何幸福在牛津
it always had been a dream to get into Oxford
一直都是 一个梦想进入牛津
I think because people had encouraged me
我想是因为人 鼓励我
and because I knew famous people having been to Oxford
因为我知道著名的 人在牛津
it is still something occasionally I
它仍然是一些偶尔我
I think about and think yes
我明白了 并认为是的
I know I could have done well
我知道我可以做得很好
I've been playing since I started at the comprehensive school
我已经从我开始玩 在综合学校
since the first year
自从第一年
I don't think I was half as clever as I was told I was, I think
我不认为我的一半 当我告诉她我很聪明，我认为
unfortunately, I grew up
不幸的是，我长大了
against a background of fairly..
背景是相当的。
of people of pretty average intellagence
的平均intellagence漂亮的人
I don't think I went to a school of bright people
我想我不去了 一所学校的聪明人
if this was the case, I don't think I would have been so big headed
如果是这样的话，我不认为 我会一直这么大的头颅
I know I went to university expecting
我知道我去大学的期望
to be something of a genius and found that wasn't the case at all
是一个天才的东西 发现并非如此
which is a good thing for me,
这对我来说是一件好事，
it's very good that I didn't count that opinion, I don't think I was
很好，我没有数 这样看来，我不认为我是
so much clever, I just think I was
所以聪明的多， 我只是觉得我是
quite enthusiastic particularly when it came to O levels
非常热情，尤其是 当它来到O水平
so I was enthusiastic about the subjects I was studying and therefore
所以我是热心的 我正在学习，因此主题
with the help of good teaching I was able to get good results
有好的教学有所帮助 我能得到好的结果
What were your results?
你的结果是什么？
well, I did well enough, I'm not going to boast
嗯，我做的够好了，我 不想拥有
No, tell me. tell me the fact. How many O levels and A levels did you get?
不，告诉我。告诉我事实。怎么用 你得到了许多层次和水平？
I got ten O levels and then
我有十个O水平并
I got four A levels
我有四一个层次
Did you get good grades within them?
你取得好成绩 在他们呢？
yes, the grades were quite satisfactory
是的，成绩 令人满意的
well I was only
我只不过是
taking university seriously for a matter of couple of months
以大学认真 短短几个月
two or three months
两个或三个月
maybe I went to the wrong university or maybe university life didn't suit me
也许我走错了大学 或是大学生活不适合我
either way
无论哪种方式
I felt a very great need to get out of the system.
我觉得非常需要 对滚出去的系统。
no formal education can prepare anybody for life
没有正式的教育 准备的人的生活
only life can prepare you for what comes
只有生命才能准备 你是什么
and sooner or later you are going to have to cross certain barriers
迟早你会 有过一定的障碍
I don't think you ever cross those uh..
我不相信你 过那些呃..
at school or at university
在学校或大学
you come across the problem of mixing with other people but
你遇到的问题 与其他人混合而
the real problem.. I mean..
真正的问题。我的意思是..
the real problem of becoming a success in the world is
成为真正的问题 在这个世界上取得成功的是
when you have to tackle yourself
当你自己处理
on the grass.. we play international wrestling
在草。我们玩 国际摔跤
yeah, that's only in summertime though
是的，那只是 在夏季，尽管
yes, only when we can to go on the grass
是的，只有当我们 可以走在草地上
being in set one, it's very very hard to keep up with the leaders
在设置一个，这是非常非常 很难跟上领导
I never have time to relax at all
我从来都没有时间放松些
I don't know what sort of stumbling blocks should be put in a child's way
我不知道什么样的绊脚石 块应放在孩子的方式
to get him used to living in the outside world
让他用 生活在外面的世界
because I think maybe this is something that was wrong in my upbringing
因为我想也许这是什么 在我的成长，是错的
I didn't have enough obstacles to get over
我没有足够的 克服障碍
I still..
我还..
I still.. set myself high standards if I'm doing something that I want to do
我还..为自己设定高标准 如果我做我想要做的事情
but that's
但这是
that's important that's not too bad a thing
这是非常重要的 不算太坏的事
But you talked also about not having enough obstacles in your life.
但你也谈到了不 在你的生活中拥有足够的障碍。
How do you feel about that now?
觉得怎么样？
funny that isn't it? I can't remember saying that but now I do remember
有趣的是，不是吗？我想不起来了 说，但现在我记得
and
和
it seems the whole situation is reversed
好像整个 相反的情况
In what way?
在哪一方面？
well now I'm a free..
现在我是一个自由的。
I've got a free hand but I've got nothing to do with myself
我有一个免费的手，但我 有与本人无关
so..
所以..
In the winter if you lived in the country
在冬季，如果 你住在乡下
it would just be all wet and there wouldn't be anything for miles around
这是潮湿的，有 不会在数英里之外的东西
and you'd get soaked if you'd try to go out
你会湿透的 如果你想出去
and there's no shelter anywhere except in  your own house
没有住所 除了在你自己的房子
but in winter you can go out on wet wintery days
但在冬天，你可以走了 在潮湿的冬天的日子
because you can always find somewhere to shelter
因为你总是可以找到 能避雨的地方
because there's lots of places
因为有太多的地方
I don't thin I've been typical of the environment in which I lived
我不薄，我是典型的 在我所生活的环境
I might still have been unemployed
我仍可能已经失业了
but what my background has given me is
但我的背景给我的是什么
umm a sense..
我感觉..
of just being part of..
只是部分的。
a very impersonal society
一个很客观的社会
the suburbs..
郊区的。
force this kind of feeling upon somebody
这种力量 感觉某人
the most you can hope to achieve is
你最希望能做到的是
is the right to climb into a suburban train
是正确的攀登 在市郊列车
five or ten times a week and just stagger back
五或十次一周 刚刚回到
for the weekend, the least is just unemployment
这个周末， 不只是失业
great, thanks
很棒，谢谢
I just needed a nice woolly pair
我只是需要一个好的羊毛对
What other things about modern society turn you off?
还有什么其他的事情 现代社会把你关掉？
the cheap satisfaction in so many things
廉价的满意度 在这么多事情
the aimlessness
漫无目标
but I think the total lack of thought is at the bottom of it
但我想，总缺乏 思想是在它的底部
nobody seems to know where they or anybody else is going
似乎没有人知道 他们或者其他人会
and nobody seems to worry
似乎没有人担心
you know, you finish the week
你知道，你完成一周
you come home, you plug into the TV set for the weekend and then you..
你回家，你插到电视 设置本周末你..
manage to get back to work on Monday
可以回到在星期一工作
and it seems to me that this is just a slow path to..
在我看来， 这是一个缓慢的路..
to.. to total brainwashing
对..总的洗脑
and if you have a brainwashed society then you're heading towards doom
如果你有一个洗脑 然后你走向毁灭的社会
there's no question about that
这是毫无疑问的
I mean, it'll be pretty tough to convince most people
我的意思是，这将是很难的 说服大多数人
that what you have here, the way you live. the way you look
那你在这里， 你的生活方式。你的样子
is better than a suburban life
比郊区生活
well, I don't want to convince anybody, I know it is
嘿.我不愿去 说服任何人，我知道这是
see, what I look like, isn't necessarily what I feel like
看，我是什么样子， 不一定是我的感觉
I not claiming that I feel as though I'm in some sort of..
我不是说我的感觉 虽然我在一些..
Nirvana
涅盘
but
但
but I'm claiming that if I lived in a bedset in suburbia, I'd be so miserable
但我认为如果我生活在一个 bedset在郊区，我会如此痛苦
I'd feel like cutting my throat
我觉得割我的喉咙
and so, there is a slight difference
因此，有一个细微的差别
when I go home
当我回家
I come.. I come in and mummy gives me a cup of tea
我来了。我进来 妈妈给了我一杯茶
and then I go out and play
然后我出去玩
and when it starts to get dark I come in again
当它开始 在黑暗中我又来了
and put on TV
和电视上放的
I don't think I was really taught any sort of policy
我不认为我是真的教 任何形式的政策
of living at all `by my parents this is probably the biggest mistake
生活在所有`父母 这可能是最大的错误
that I was just left to fend for myself in a world which
我只是自生自灭 对于自己在这个世界上
they seem completely oblivious of
他们似乎完全忘记了
and I found even when I tried to discuss problems which were facing me in school
我发现当我试图讨论 这是我在学校所面临的问题
my parents didn't seem to be aware of the nature of the problem
我的父母似乎没有 意识到问题的本质
we.. we made up
我们..我们和好了
quite.. quite well after..
相当。很好..
the bad times we went through when I was in my early twenties
不好的时候，我们经历了 当我在我二十出头
there's still.. there are still awkward patches
还有..有 还是尴尬的补丁
but
但
I think suddenly
我突然想到
perhaps almost mutually, it dawned upon us that
也许几乎相互，它 想到我们，
we were all making mistakes
我们都犯错误
and
和
and also that some of the things we did couldn't be helped
同时，一些 我们并不能帮助的事情
and
和
i think now
我想现在
perhaps the greatest thing we achieved is
也许最大的 我们取得了
we know when to say nothing
我们知道什么时候什么也不说
and we know when to do nothing and we know when to be tolerant of each other
我们知道，我们什么也不做 知道什么时候要宽容对方
and that's a great thing
这是一种伟大的事情
that's really tremendous
这真是巨大的
what I'd like most of all would be
我最喜欢的是
would be to be able to
将能够
to do something for my parents
为我的父母做些什么
when they are older, to be there when..
当他们长大的时候， 当..
when the time.. if necessary
当时间。 如果必要的话
Were they upset with what you said about them in the last program?
他们烦你 说他们在过去的计划？
I'm sure they were
我敢肯定他们
but I..
但我。
I don't wish I hadn't said it
我不希望我没说
because I said exactly what was going through my mind
因为我说的究竟是什么 在我的脑海
I think I was very venomous
我认为我是非常有毒的
and I think I
我想我
had I been in an easier situation myself
如果我是一个更容易的情况下自己
had I had less worries, myself at the time
当时的我不担心， 我的时间
I would have been perhaps a little kinder
我会一直 也许仁慈一点
I had to take out my anger on somebody and I think it came out on my parents
我不得不接受我的愤怒的人 我认为这是我的父母
but perhaps unconsciously a lot of what I said was what I did feel underneath
但也许不知不觉的很多东西 我说的是什么，我觉得下面
but
但
but I don't want the scar to remain
但我不想瘢痕保持
when I get married, I don't want to have any children
我结婚时，我不 想有孩子
because
因为
because they are always doing naughty things and making the whole house untidy
因为他们总是做淘气的 的东西，使整个房子不整洁的
I always told myself that umm..
我总是告诉自己，嗯..
I would never have children
我将永远不会有孩子
Why?
为什么呢？
because..
因为..
well, because..
嗯，因为..
children inherit something from their parents
孩子们继承的东西 从他们的父母
and even if my wife were the most
即使我的妻子是最
high spirited and ordinary and normal of people
昂扬的普通 与正常人
the child would still stand a fairly good chance of being not totally
孩子仍有相当 不完全的好机会
full of happiness
充满幸福
because of what he or she will have inherited from me
因为他或她 将要继承我的
poor people, I don't like them very much
可怜的人，我不很喜欢他们
no, it's the ghostly colored people
不，这是可怕的有色人种
if you think of a purple person with red eyes and yellow feet
如果你认为一个紫色的人 有红色的眼睛和黄脚
I can't really think of what they really look like
我真的想不起来 他们看起来真的像
What goes through your mind when you look at those two films?
你脑子里在想什么的时候 看那两个电影？
When you are seven, bright and perky?
当你七岁的时候，开朗、活泼的？
I find it hard to believe that I was ever like that but there's the evidence
我很难相信我 以前喜欢，但有证据
I wonder why I was like that I wonder what it was
我不知道为什么我是这样的 我不知道那是什么
inside me that made me like that
在我，让我这样
and I can even see at fourteen that I was beginning to get more subdued
我甚至可以看到在十四 我开始更柔和
and I was putting a lot more thought into what I was saying
我将更多的思想 为我在说什么
to a ridiculous degree
一个荒谬的程度
and probably when I was seven..
也许当我是七。
I lived in a wonderful world where everything was sensation
我生活在一个美好的世界 那里的一切感觉
and I could be happy obviously but be miserable the next minute
我可以快乐的明显 但下一刻痛苦
I know at seven years old I was fascinated by everything around me
我知道七岁时的我 着迷于我周围的一切
the colors of things and things that were funny
事物的颜色和 的东西是有趣的
sounds that things made
听起来这东西了
I had, if you like, idiosyncratic views
我有，如果你喜欢，特殊的意见
about things that other people hadn't even thought about
的事情，其他 人们还没有想过
I remember I thought colored people had purple noses and green legs
我记得我认为有色人种 有紫色的鼻子和绿色的腿
or something like that
或类似的东西
perhaps I'm still looking for..
也许我还在寻找。
it's difficult to explain,
这很难解释，
the green nose and this sort of thing
绿色的鼻子，这类事情
and I know that..
我知道..
that they are still there that when you look at a human being
他们还在那里 当你看着一个人类
there's more.. there's more to that person then..
还有更多的。有 更多的人了。
just a.. just a robot
就好了。只是一个机器人
when I grow up I want to be an astronaut
当我长大后我想成为一名宇航员
but if I can't be an astronaut I think I'll be a coach driver
但是如果我不能成为一名宇航员 我想我会成为一个教练司机
this probably linked up now with the fact that I want to travel
这可能是联系起来了 事实上，我想去旅行
my thoughts haven't really changed
我的思想并没有真正改变
I definitely would like to be a coach driver now
我肯定会喜欢的 是一个教练司机现在
I suppose I..
我想我。
yes, well..
是的，好的。
I would like to be somebody in a position of importance
我想成为的人 在一个位置的重要性
and I've always thought this..
我一直认为这..
but I don't think I'm the right sort of person to carry the responsibility
但我不认为我是正确的 人承担责任
for whatever it is I always thought, well, I'd love to be in
不管它是什么我总是 想，嗯，我想是
possibly even love to be in politics
甚至喜欢在政治
something like this
像这样的东西
but
但
I suppose I'd find it just as tedious as all of the other jobs I've done so..
我想我会发现它一样乏味 所有我做的其他工作等。
there were things I always thought I could do
有些事情我 一直以为我可以做的
I could give lectures on..
我可以讲的。
erudite subjects I'd read all about
博学者我读过的所有关于
I could work in the theatre
我会在剧院工作的
perhaps lighting or
也许照明或
directing a show
演出的指挥
And is all of that lost to you?
都是那个失去了你？
does seem to be, yes
似乎，是的
I don't see anyway out, I've thought of everything I possibly could
我不知道怎么了，我想 我的一切都有可能
it seemed to me for a long time that getting a reliable job
在我看来，很长一段时间 得到一个可靠的工作
and a nice place to live would be the solution
和一个生活的好地方 将解决方案
well, I haven't succeeded
嗯，我还没有成功
I can't see any immediate future at all
我根本看不到任何直接的未来
but
但
here I am, I'm still
我在这里，我还是
I've still got clothes on my back
我仍然在我的背上有衣服
not particularly nice clothes but I've still got them
不是特别漂亮的衣服 但我仍然得到了他们
I have a place to go to
我有一个要去的地方
I have some prospects of work, I'm still applying for jobs, I haven't given up
我有一些工作的前景，我仍然 申请工作，我没有放弃
I think, I think I'm lucky because I have met so many people
我想，我想我很幸运 因为我遇见了许多人
I've worked with people who have no future whatsoever
和我一起工作的人 没有未来可言
for whom life is finished completely at fifty
他们的生活结束了 完全五十
and yet somehow they have to keep going
然而，他们必须继续保持
and
和
I don't want it to seem that I'm complaining too much
我不想让它看起来 我抱怨太多
I feel, especially sometimes when I'm on my own
我感觉，尤其是当我在 我自己
that I'm loosing touch with where people live
我失去了联系 随着人们居住的地方
Do you worry about your sanity?
你担心你的理智？
other people sometimes worry about it
其他人会担心
Like who?
喜欢谁？
as I've said, I
我已经说过了，我
sometimes can be found
有时可以发现
behaving in an erratic fashion
在一个不稳定的行为方式
sometimes I can get very frustrated, very angry
有时我会很 沮丧，非常生气
for no apparent reason, for a reason which won't be apparent
没有明显的原因，为 这不会很明显的原因
to other people around me
我周围的其他人
it's happened from time to time
它发生的时间
Have you had treatment?
你有没有治疗？
I've occasionally had to see doctors, yes
我偶尔 去看医生，是的
I haven't had any treatment
我没有任何治疗
And what have they said to you?
他们有什么说的吗？
I've had a lot of advice but you know the best medicine is..
我有很多的建议 但你知道最好的药物是..
kind words
亲切的话语
and it usually comes
它通常是
from somebody who has nothing to do with the medical profession
从某人无关 随着医疗行业
which isn't to say that doctor's can't be very helpful
这并不是说医生的 不可能是很有帮助的
but really, the thing a sick person wants
但说真的，这件事 一个生病的人
is to be away from doctors as soon as possible
是要离开的 医生尽快
What did they say was wrong with you?
他们说什么了吗？
well, I have always had a nervous complain
嗯，我一直有一个紧张 抱怨
I've had it since I was sixteen
我已经因为我是十六
it was responsible for my leaving university
这是负责的 我离开大学
and some of my difficulties with work
和我的一些困难的工作
but as you know, you can't avoid to go around looking depressed
但你知道，你不能避免 四处寻找沮丧
that in itself is bad enough
这本身已经够糟糕了
So can you lick it?
所以你可以舔吗？
it remains to be seen
它仍然可以看到
yes, I'd say I believed in god
是的，我会说我相信上帝
Are you religious?
你信教吗？
well, I go to church with my parents on Sundays
好的，我去教堂 在星期天我的父母
I don't know now whether I believe in god or not
我不知道现在是否 我相信或不相信上帝
I thought an awful lot about it actually and I still don't know
我想很多事情其实 我还不知道
but still I'm certain, if one were to survive in this world
但我确信，如果有人 在这个世界上生存
they'd have to believe in god
他们相信上帝
I don't think of god as a creature but I think of..
我不认为上帝是一个 生物但我想..
something..
什么东西。
time.. destiny..
时间。的命运。
which is regulating everybody's affairs and witch you cannot
这是调节大家的事务 你不能和女巫
you cannot fight against and you cannot..
你不能反对 你不能。
order about
命令
And how has he been treating you?
以及他如何对待你？
well I said to somebody lasy week
我对别人说他星期
that I preferred The Old Testament to The New Testament
我喜欢旧约 在新约圣经
because in The Old Testament
因为在旧约
god is very unpredictable
上帝是不可预料的
and that's, I think, how I see him in my life
而且，我认为， 我如何在我的生活中看到他
sometimes very benevolent
有时很仁慈
sometimes, seemingly, needlessly unkind
有时，看似无情的，不必要的
If we come back in seven years, how would you like us to find you?
如果我们在七年回来，怎么 你要我们来找你？
In a job, for which I was getting satisfaction
在一个工作，这 我得到满足
married
结婚
probably with children
可能有孩子
with
随着
a good salary
一个好的工资
enough to, as I said before, live fairly comfortably
足够的，就像我之前说的， 相当舒适的生活
and with fiends whom I could contact if I wanted to
与恶魔的人 如果我想我可以联系
I'm a lot happier now, than I was seven years ago
我很开心， 我比七年前
I'm more content, I don't have such dreadful yearnings
我更多的内容，我不 有这种可怕的渴望
I don't feel so hopelessly as if everything is against me
我不觉得如此绝望 如果一切都是反对我
Do you think, what a waste?
你认为，什么是浪费？
yeah, perhaps
是啊，也许
Why should you accept this?
你为什么要接受这个？
You're better than all of this aren't you?
你比 所有这一切，不是吗？
I'm not better than anything or anybody
我不比任何人或任何事
I'm just somebody with my own particular difficulties
我只是某人 我自己的特别的困难
and my own particular obstacles to select
和我自己 选择特定的障碍
and everybody else is doing exactly the same thing
和其他人都在做的事情 同样的事情
if we did all love Jeffery and all wanted to marry him
如果我们都爱他 所有想嫁给他
-yes! -I think I'd know the one he'd like
-是的！ 我想我知道他想
Jackie, Lynn, Susan
杰基琳恩苏珊
After primary school they separated
小学毕业后他们分开
and at fourteen Lynn was at grammar school
十四岁的琳恩 在文法学校
and Jackie and Susan were at comprehensive.
杰基和苏珊 在综合。
we had a teacher at school
我们在学校里有一个老师
his favorite ploy was
他最喜欢的活动是
all you girls want to do is walk out, get married, have babies
你们都想走出去， 结婚了，有孩子
and push a pram down the street with a fag hanging outside your mouth
和推一辆婴儿车走在街上，一个 FAG挂在你的嘴
women are expanding into so many different areas now that
妇女正在扩大到如此 许多不同的领域，现在
it must be getting easier
它必须变得更容易
Susan has been married four years and has a son of two.
苏珊已经结婚四年了 有两个儿子。
Her husband Billy is a gas fitter
她的丈夫比利是一种气体钳工
and they live in a council house in the east end of London.
他们生活在一个委员会 在伦敦东区的房子。
75!
75！
I'm lucky I expect because I still manage to..
我很幸运，我希望 因为我仍然设法..
to do my own thing, I've got a husband who lets me do what I want
做我自己的事，我有一个丈夫 谁让我做我想做的事
and a mum who helps me out
和妈妈谁帮我了
you know, and I do a little part time job
你知道我是关心的 一小部分时间工作
which is enough for me because I don't think I could cope with a full time job
这对我来说足够了因为我不 我想我能应付一个全职工作
and I wouldn't want to personally
我不想亲自
60!
60！
Jackie was married at 19 and her husband is a decorator
19岁的杰基结婚了 她的丈夫是一个装饰
She works for an insurance company in the city
她在一家 在市保险公司
I certainly don't want to stay in the position I am at the moment
我当然不想呆在这 我现在的位置
forever and ever
永远永远
but how ambitious, I'm not really sure
但如何雄心勃勃的，我真的不知道
tends to..
倾向于..
change as you get older so..
改变你变老，所以..
just got to wait and see really
只是等着去看看真的
Lynn also married at 19,
琳恩也19岁结的婚，
her husband works at the post office and they have two daughters.
她的丈夫在邮局工作 他们有两个女儿。
They moved out of the Eastend to Kent 18 months ago.
他们离开了伦敦东区肯特 18个月前。
I'm going to work in Woolworth's
我打算在伍尔沃思的工作
At 21 Lynn was working in a mobile library in Tower Hamlets
21岁的琳恩是在一个移动的工作 在伦敦塔桥图书馆
she's still there.
她还在那儿。
- have I stamped yours? - yes
-我戳你的吗？ -是
I've not stamped yours
我不上你的
Sleeping Beauty
睡美人
teaching children the beauty of books
教育儿童书籍之美
and watching their faces
看他们的脸
as books unfold to them
书展现给他们
is just fantastic
真是太棒了
to work with children of that age you've got to love them and I love children
在那个年龄的孩子你的工作 要爱他们，我爱孩子
but I know he loves her and he loves her
但是我知道他很爱她 他爱她
- I don't, I love him!
我不，我爱他！
I don't think I'd..
我不想我的。
get married too early
结婚太早
I'd like to have a full life first and
我想有一个完整的 人生的第一次，
- you'd like to enjoy yourself before? - meet people.. yeah
你想享受自己之前？ 满足的人。是啊
before you commit yourself to a family
在你提交你自己 一个家庭
if you think that
如果你认为
getting married, as far as we are concerned is a case of
结婚，只要我们 关注是一例
going to work come home cook tea for hubby go to bed getting up going to work
去工作，回家煮茶 老公睡觉起床去工作
you're totally mistaken
你完全弄错了
Did you meet enough men before you decided who you wanted to marry?
你遇到过足够的人在你面前 决定你想结婚吗？
I've been married a year and..
我已经结婚一年了。
a couple of months
两个月
you do think, christ, what have I done?
你真的认为，基督，什么 我做了什么？
- see I've still got my... - and I'm being honest about it!
看看我还有我的… -我是诚实的呢！
I think it's the same... you think, christ, what have I done?
我认为这是一样的…你 认为，基督，我都做了些什么？
it is a partnership marriage, yes
它是一种伙伴关系的婚姻，是的
we were married, i'd say obviously, young
我们结婚了， 我想说，很明显，年轻的
but because we wanted to go out and have fun together
但因为我们想出去 一起玩
and grow together
共同成长
I'm not sure I would recommend it
我不确定我会推荐它
I think if...
我想如果…
but again you are generalizing, I mean if..
但你又 对，我的意思是如果..
I would say on average
我会说平均
19 is probably too young
19可能是太年轻了
I've had a good time up till I was 24
我有一个很好的时间 直到我24岁
and
和
and I think that to get married young
我认为结婚的年轻
there must be things that you miss, you must miss that crucial stage
一定有东西，你错过了， 你必须错过关键阶段
of being yourself
做你自己
because the minute you get married, you're no longer
因为你 结婚，你不再
a single being
一个单一的人
you're a partnership and that should be the idea behind it
你的伙伴， 应该是其背后的思想
if I could, I would have two girls and two boys - yeah, so would I
如果我可以，我会有两个女孩 两个男孩-是的，我也这么想
And what about you Jackie?
你呢，杰基？
my mum... because she's got five girls, she's got seven years bad luck
我的妈妈…因为她有五 女孩，她有七年的坏运气
that's why she's got five girls
这就是为什么她有五个女孩
I'd like to be able..
我想能..
to have a happy family
有一个幸福的家庭
I mean I know that it's not possible to happy all of the time
我的意思是我知道它的 不可能快乐所有的时间
but as much of the time as was possible
但大部分时间是可能的
go through there, that's the nursery
经过那里，那是幼儿园
-got any plans -oh, do me a favor
-有什么计划 哦，帮我一个忙
at 21 Jackie had moved into a new house
21岁的杰基已经进入 一个新的房子
she has decided not to have any children
她已经决定不再有孩子
basically, I would say because I am far too selfish
基本上，我会说，因为 我太自私了
I enjoy
我喜欢
doing what I want, when I want and how I want and..
做我想做的事，当我 想和我多么想和..
certainly at the moment I..
当然，此刻的我。
can't see any way around that
无法看到任何方式
that's not to say that's a forever decision
这并不是说 这是一个永远的决定
some people can make it work, I just don't think I could
有些人可以使它的工作，我 想我也不会
You don't think you're missing out on what they have?
你不认为你错过了 对他们有什么？
Their stake in the future?
他们在未来的股权？
no..
没有。
that's a very... that's a terrible way to put it, you know
这是一个非常…这是一个可怕的 这么说，你知道的
I mean, that makes you sound like you're saying
我的意思是，那是你 听起来像是你说的
"right, great, we're going to have a child"
“好，好，我们 要有一个孩子”
and that.. that's us
和..这就是我们
I do feel to a degree that yes I am missing out
我真的感觉到一定程度， 是的我错过了
but I think I also get far more
但我想我也获得更多
pleasure out of
高兴的
I'm gaining far more experience by not having that tie
我获得了更多的经验 没有那条领带
when I got married
也跟我结婚时一样
the primary reason was because I
主要的原因是因为我
wanted to have a child the two, to me, went together
想要一个孩子 两个，我，一起去的
I can understand Jackie's decision because
我能理解杰基的决定 因为
I think there is sill a lot of pressure put on
我认为有窗台 压力很大
young married couples to have children as though it was expected of them
年轻夫妻有孩子 虽然它是对他们的期望
and I think it's all wrong, it's just a personal decision
我认为这是错误的，它只是一个 个人的决定
that everyone is entitled to make
每个人都有权向
and knowing what it does to your life I can
知道它 对你的生活我可以
fully understand someone who decides not to
充分了解某人 他决定不
what would you do if you had lots of money about..
如果你想做什么 你有许多钱
I would by me self a new house, you know
我会用我的自我 一个新的房子，你知道的
one that's all nice and comfy
一个很好的，舒适的
Do you get depressed by money problems?
你拿到钱的问题沮丧？
no, why?
不，为什么？
why should you?
你为什么要这么做呢？
if can manage with what you got? -it's easy to get depressed over money
如果能和你有什么安排吗？ 使沮丧的钱很容易
-it's so easy to but why should you?
-很容易但是你为什么？
- why bother about it - when I reach the 18th day of the month
为什么要费心了 当我到达一个月的第十八天
when my mortgage is due on the 20th
当我的按揭贷款是由于在第二十
and there's nowhere near enough money in there
有没有 在有足够的钱
I get depressed about it obviously
让我沮丧了很明显
what money?
什么钱？
it was hard, first of all, when I gave up work from having a fairly high salary
这是很难的，首先，我给 从具有相当高的薪水的工作
to nothing was hard
没有什么是困难的
but you get used to it whatever your circumstances are
但你得习惯它 无论你的情况
you live in them, you get used to it, you cope, everybody does
你住在那里，你习惯它， 你应付，大家都是
I think before going to a grammar school, I just
我想去之前 文法学校，我只是
you know, comprehensive school
你知道，综合学校
it just seem more friendly, you know, and at the time it was but now
它只是看起来更友好，你知道的， 在当时这是现在
now they are really different
现在，他们真的是不同的
-grammar schools are fantastic -if you say so
语法学校很棒 如果你这么说的话
we've heard that it doesn't scratch the bottom, why am I using
我们听说它不 刮底，为什么我使用
wooden spoon please? to stir this saucepan..
木勺子吗？ 搅拌这锅..
I don't think anybody influenced me, it was a conscious decision
我不认为任何人的影响 我，是一个有意识的决定
obviously, the decision
显然，决策
was discussed at home
讨论了在家里
but
但
it was always in me
它总是在我
to go
去
there may come a time, perhaps later on when I regret
可能会有一个时间，也许 后来当我后悔
not having..
没有..
we are talking about examination results really, that's what it boils down to
我们谈论的是检查结果 真的，那就是把它归结为
and.. I got..
和..我有。
and I got some examination results and O levels and GCSEs or whatever
我有一些检查结果 O水平和普通中等教育证书或什么的
I didn't need them
我不需要他们
for the jobs I decided to do, so
这工作我做决定，所以
with this school, we do metal work and woodwork
这个学校，我们做的 金属制品和木制品
and the boys do cookery
和孩子们做烹饪
and we get a share of everything.. sort of thing
我们得到一份 的一切。这种事
most parents would want
大多数父母希望
every advantage they can get for their child, now
每一个优势，他们可以 让自己的孩子，现在
whether you class going to grammar school as an advantage
无论你班去 文法学校作为一个优势
is dependent on you entire outlook
依赖于你的整个世界观
if you don't
要是找不到呢
class it as an advantage then you are not going to push that
这是一种优势，那么你的班 是不是要把这
my mum left me, she knew I could go to grammar
我妈妈离开了我，她知道 我可以去语法
and
和
and I decided that I didn't want to
我决定，我不想
she encouraged me in the choice that I made and
她鼓励我 我的选择了
right or wrong that was my choice
对或错，是我的选择
as much as I was capable of making a decision
尽我所能 决策
and
和
I enjoyed myself
我喜欢我自己
my father recently go education, he never went to the local comprehensive
我父亲最近去教育，他 不要去当地的综合
but at the same time
但在同一时间
I don't think he was too worried which way I was decided to go
我认为他不太担心 我决定走哪条路
I think he probably knew me better than I did
我认为他可能知道 我比我做的更好
which was basically, I was a very lazy person academically
这是基本的，我是一个 在学术上很懒的人
and I think I would have found grammar school bullshit
我想我会 发现语法学校的废话
Do you have any regrets about it?
你对它有什么遗憾？
umm.. no, no
嗯..不，没有
you can only have regrets about things if you're not happy with the way you are
你只会后悔的事情 如果你不喜欢你的方式
You look at the old film and you see yourselves as seven,
你看老电影，你看 你们七个，
do you think you've changed?
你认为你已经改变了吗？
no, I don't think I have really
不，我不认为我真的
we're the same people as we were then
我们同样的人，我们就
I was always chatty, Jackie was always chatty
我总是喋喋不休， 杰基很健谈
and Lynn was always the quieter one
琳恩一直安静的人
But is that depressing or frightening to think
但是，郁闷 或是很可怕的
we're all set by the time we're seven and that's it?
我们所有的时间 我们是七，是吗？
I don't think one's set by that age, you progress
我不认为人的设置 在那个年龄，你的进步
but
但
the overall character is there to come up
总体特征 有来了
I think the basics are there
我想基本都有
yeah, the basics are there
是的，基本都有
But why is it that you three haven't changed so much do you think?
但为什么你三 没有改变了这么多，你觉得呢？
- we'll probably never no that - I think we've all had
我们可能永远都不会不 我想我们都有
we've all had a stable background with stable relationships all the way through
我们都有一个稳定的背景 稳定的关系，所有的方式通过
the same people are there now that were there then
现在有相同的人 在那
the poor, if you don't help then soon they'll sort of
可怜的，如果你不帮助 他们很快会之类的
die soon, wouldn't they?
快死了，不是吗？
well, some people are just born into rich families and they're lucky
嗯，有些人只是出世 在富裕的家庭，他们是幸运的
I don't see why they should have to luck when people have worked all their lives
我不明白他们为什么要有运气 当人们都在工作，他们的生活
and haven't got half as much as what they have
并没有得到半 当他们有很多
it just doesn't seem fair
这也太不公平了
I've had the opportunities in life that I've wanted
我有机会 在生活中，我所要的
- I'll say I've had more! - yeah, you..
我会说我有！ 是的，你。
So you three working class girls don't feel
所以你三个工作班 女孩不觉得
bitter about a society
一个社会的苦
that maybe gives one strata of it more opportunities than another?
也许提供了一个阶层的 比另一个更多的机会吗？
no
没有
not bitter
不苦
not at all
一点也不
I don't event think, to be honest, we consciously think about it
我不认为事件，说实话， 我们有意识的思考
until this program comes up once every seven years
直到这个程序 上每七年一次
I really don't think we even think about it
我真的不想 我们甚至想它
I don't not sit there thinking
我没有坐在那里思考
"he actually was born into money!"
“他真的是出世到钱！”
"he's had more opportun.."
“他有更多的机会”。
I mean it just doesn't even cross my mind
我的意思是，它只是不 即使我的脑海
I think we all could have gone in whatever way we wanted to at the time
我认为我们都应该去 任何我们想要的的时候
within our capabilities, I mean
我们的能力范围内，我的意思是
we chose our own jobs
我们选择了自己的工作
we were able to chose our own jobs quite freely
我们可以选择我们的 自己的工作很自由
if you've got a comfortable background then perhaps it can make life easy
如果你已经有了一个舒适的背景 或许它能让生活变得轻松
but I think you've also seen
但我想你也看到了
within this program that it doesn't always work that way
在这个程序，它 不总是这样的
In some respects
在某些方面
I think that..
我认为。
the boys and Suzi
男孩苏子
didn't have
没有
didn't have such an open choice as we had
没有这样一个 我们已经开放的选择
it was mapped out for such an early age as to where they were going
这是描绘出了这样的一个早期 年龄是他们要去的地方
and
和
and they had to live up
他们住在
it's a hard thing living up to parental..
这是一个很难的事情 辜负父母的。
- expectations
预期
before I'm old and that, enough to get a job
在我老去之前， 能得到一份工作
I'll just walk around
我就走
and see what I can find
看看我能找到什么
I was going to be a film star but..
我要成为一个电影明星，但是..
now I'm going to be an electrical engineer
现在我要做 一个电气工程师
which is more to reality, really
这是更现实的，真的
I often say I'm saving to settle down with Yvonne
我常说我节省 伊冯安顿下来
and then I think to myself "nah I might buy a car instead"
然后我想“呐 我会买一辆汽车而不是”
since 21
自21
I've got married
我已经结婚了
had a couple of kids
有一个孩子的夫妇
and um..
嗯..
well, I don't think there's anybody else I could have ever married except Yvonne
嗯，我不认为有任何人 我曾经结婚，除了伊冯
it gives me my life really because
它给我的生活真的是因为
we're together, we have the children and everything
我们在一起，我们有 孩子们和所有的一切
And what is it with Yvonne that you fell in love with?
它是什么伊冯 你爱上了吗？
her nature, really
她的天性，真的
it's always quite thoughtful
它总是很体贴
except when she's laughing
但当她笑
Tell me, do you have any girlfriends?
告诉我，你有女朋友吗？
well, not many
好了，不多
What do you thing about girls?
你有什么事呢？
oh, not much
哦，不多
When you decided to have the five, did you want to have them close together?
当你决定要做五， 你想让他们接近？
yeah
是啊
because if you separated your kids and say one is fifteen and one is six
因为如果你分开你的孩子 说是十五和六
such an age gap that they could never get on
这样的年龄差距 他们可能不会
they'd never grow up together, they won't know each other
他们从来没有在一起长大， 他们不了解对方
Why did you want to have a large family?
你为什么想 一个大家庭吗？
well I wouldn't really call it a large family
我不会真的 称它为一个大家庭
Well, I think it is large by average standards.
嗯，我认为这是大 按平均标准。
yeah?
是啊？
we just wanted five kids
我们只想要五个孩子
you know, we got exactly what we want, three boys and two girls
你知道，我们得到了我们想要的东西， 三个男孩和两个女孩
no, no... that's exactly... it's a handful, you know
不，不行。这正是… 这是一把，你知道的
Do you push your kids at school?
你把你的 孩子们在学校吗？
Those that go to school already?
那些去 学校了吗？
no, I don't push them, I encourage them in what..
不，我不把它们， 我鼓励他们在什么..
when they come home and I come home in the evening
当他们回家 我晚上回家
they tell me what they've done
他们告诉我他们都做了什么
and if they've done anything bad I tell them where they've gone wrong
如果他们做了什么 我告诉他们，他们做错了
and if they..
如果他们..
want um..
想..
what's the word? not encouragement.. praise
我不明白你的意思？ 不鼓励的。赞美
for what they've done
为他们做了什么
then I'll give it to them if they've done well, yeah
然后我就给他们 如果他们做得很好，是的
Do you see maybe your kids are going to be smarter than you are?
你看到你的孩子 要比你聪明吗？
well, yeah there's a couple of them already that are gonna be smarter
嗯，是有几个人 已经是要聪明
How are you going to handle that?
你打算如何处理？
um...
嗯…
I'll keep them on my side
我会让他们在我的身边
they say, "where's your father, then?"
他们说，“你的父亲，然后呢？”
you know, when your mum's out at work instead of your father
你知道，当你的妈妈在工作 而不是你的父亲
I just tell'em I ain't got one
我刚才主持人说我没有一个
What effect has that had on you?
这对你有什么影响？
well, I don't think it's had any effect on me because
嗯，我不认为有任何 对我的影响，因为
what you don't have you don't miss
你没有的你不要错过
twenty years ago
二十年前了
when I was born, you know, an illegitimate child that's..
当我出世，你知道，一个 非婚生孩子的。
something that is only whispered about
这仅仅是传言
people
的人
you know, feel
你知道，感觉
feel strongly about it in those days but nowadays..
强烈的感觉 在那些日子里，但现在..
it's..
它的。
it's not a serious matter
这不是一个严重的问题
the serious point is whether you stay with somebody or you leave them
严重的问题是你是否会继续 与某人或你离开他们
What would you like to give your children that you never had?
你想给你的是什么 孩子，你从未有过的？
they've got everything
他们所拥有的一切
they've even got what I never had
他们甚至还有什么我没有
so..
所以..
- Which is what? - a father, isn't it?
这是什么？ 一个父亲，不是吗？
so, I mean, they've had everything
所以，我的意思是，他们已经拥有一切
I feel like bundling when there's already a.. when there's already a fight
我喜欢捆绑的时候 已经A.。如果已经有战斗
Simon was brought up in a children's home.
西蒙是一个长大的 儿童之家。
He went back to live with his mother when he was thirteen.
他回到住 他的母亲在他十三岁的时候。
I was at a boarding school and I liked the discipline
我在一所寄宿学校， 我喜欢的学科
it gave me a kind of freedom2
它给我一种freedom2
Do you encourage that with your children?
你的鼓励 与你的孩子吗？
yeah, I like to encourage that, they go to bed the same time every night
是的，我想鼓励他们去， 睡觉每天晚上同一时间
and they get up round about the same time every morning
他们得到了周围 每天同一时间
and they go to school the same time everyday
他们去学校
you know, it's good to have discipline and routine
你知道，这是很好的 有纪律和常规
But what about in your life? Do you think there has been too routine?
但对你的生活？做 你认为已经太习惯？
no, not really
不太感兴趣
I mean, somebody else might think so yeah but I enjoy
我的意思是，别人会这么想 是的，我喜欢
having a routine and I enjoyed knowing where I was going to be next
有一个常规的和我喜欢知道 我要去哪里下
and what I had to do next
我下一步该做什么
because that sort of relieved me from responsibilities
因为那种如释重负 我的责任
At 21 he was working in the freezer room of Wall's Sausages in London.
21岁的他是在冷冻室工作 在伦敦和路雪香肠。
How do you see the future? As far as work goes.
你怎么看未来？ 就工作而言。
well, I know I can't stay at Wall's forever, I mean, this is just not me
好的，我知道我不能留在和路雪 我的意思是，这是永远的，不是我
I couldn't stay there for that long, my mind would go dead
我不能呆在那里 那么长的时间，我会去死
how long have I been there? about eight or nine years or something like that
我在那儿多久了？约八 或九年，或类似的东西
there's a lot of people I know there now when I first went there, I mean...
有很多人我知道现在 当我第一次去那里，我的意思是…
it's getting to know people, now
这是认识人，现在
that I've been there so long, I know practically everybody who's in there
我已经有很长时间了，我知道 几乎每个人都谁在那里
now I don't think my mind will go dead because I have a lot to talk about
现在，我不认为我会死的 因为我有很多话要说
everyday go to work, you know there's always
每天去上班， 你知道，总是有
somebody says something smart, you know
有人说，聪明的，你知道的
someday..
有一天..
I'll be just like anybody else
我会跟其他人一样
nothing too marvelous
没什么了不起的
I feel okay just getting on with life
我觉得还好刚刚与生活
just sort of keeping up
只是保持排序
but I know if I really wanted to I could get on
但我知道，如果我真的想 我会在
it would only take a little spark in me to do it
这将只需要一点火花 在我做的
I'm quite happy to stay there
我很乐意呆在那里
doesn't look like it's going to close down, so, I mean
看来没法 关闭，所以，我的意思是
better the devil you know, isn't it
更好的魔鬼你知道吗，不是吗
Do you ever feel you should be doing better jobs than these?
你是否觉得你应该做的 比这更好的工作？
Aren't you worth more than this?
你不值得这样做吗？
no, I haven't really
不，我真的没有
I suppose I just like hard work, I don't know
我想我就像 努力工作，我不知道
but um..
但是，嗯..
it's never really
这是从来没有真正
sort of worried me
有点担心我
I suppose it should, but it just doesn't
我想它应该，但它只是不
not really interested in moving up
动了真的不感兴趣
up the scale
上升音阶
why?
为什么呢？
I don't need the hassle of being a
我不需要再做
charger or the manager or whatever
充电器或经理或什么的
I had a dream when
我有一个梦想当
when all the world was on top of me
当全世界都在我身上
and
和
and everything was... and I just about got out
一切都是… 我只是出去了
and everything flew in the air
一切都在空中飞的
and it all landed on my head
所有这一切都落在我的头上
see, I mean everybody's got the same start
看，我的意思是每个人都有 一开始
they've got that little bit of grey matter in their head
他们已经得到了一点 他们头脑中的灰质
and it depends how they use it
这取决于怎样使用它
and for what purpose
为了什么目的
yeah, if you're just going to be like me and take it easy for you life
是的，如果你要和我一样 放松你的生活
if you're going to be somebody who really wants to go far
如果你想成为的人 谁真的想走远
well you have to push yourself
你要把自己
if you don't push yourself, you won't go up
如果你不把自己， 你不去了
And did you want to go far? Push yourself?
你想走多远？ 把你自己吗？
um...
嗯…
no, I want to get through life nice and easy
不，我想 通过生活很容易
Simon and his family live in a Council Flat in Southwold, London
西蒙和他的家人住在 在索思沃尔德委员会平，伦敦
What do you think about rich people?
你认为有钱人？
well..
好的。
not much
不多
Tell me about them.
告诉我关于他们的事。
well they think they can do everything without you doing it as well
他们认为他们可以做所有的事 没有你做的好
rich people, they have all different things
有钱的人，他们有 所有不同的东西
they have everything they want whereas poor people
他们有他们想要的一切 而可怜的人
they don't have nothing and they know they haven't got nothing
他们什么也没有 他们知道他们还没什么
and so they know they are missing something
所以他们知道 他们失去了一些东西
What are you missing?
你缺少了什么？
well, I'm missing a bike and
嗯，我丢失的自行车
a fishing rod
钓鱼竿
Are you envious of people who have a lot of money?
你是嫉妒的人 他有很多钱吗？
no, I may have been but
不，我可能已经但
I can't envy them now because
我不羡慕他们现在因为
I've got what I want so
我已经得到我想要的那样
there's nothing that anyone can give me that's going to make me any happier
没有任何人能给 我会让我更快乐
I could save for months and then one day just go out and spend it
我能保存几个月后 有一天，只是去花掉它
and that's that I would feel quite happy about it
这就是我会 很高兴
I wouldn't worry about getting the next penny
我不担心 如何让下一分钱
if you don't plan anything, you'll never get by anyway
如果你没有任何计划， 你将永远得不到的呢
you could have millions and you wouldn't know what to do with it
你可以上你 不知道怎么用
if you just keep spending it, you have to know what you are spending
如果你只是把它花，你有 知道你的开支
everybody's gotta get used to
每个人都会习惯的
knowing colored people
知道的人
and colored people in turn have got to get used to
反过来，有色人种 不得不习惯
being with white people
与白人
because if either side doesn't work properly
因为如果任何一方 工作不正常
then no side will work properly
然后边没有正常工作
they're just the same as me aren't they?
他们为我不也一样吗？
I mean, do you think it's hard being a black man in English society today?
我的意思是，你认为是很难的 一个在英国社会的黑人男子今天？
It depends what you want, isn't it?
这取决于你想要的，不是吗？
if you just want to life in the society, no it's not hard
如果你只是想生活在 社会，不难
if you want to fight the society, yes it would be hard
如果你想打架的社会， 是的很难
And have you ever wanted to fight it?
你想打架吗？
not really, no there's no need for it
不，没有 不需要它
I've been to Madame Tussauds with my mum
我去了杜莎夫人 我的妈妈
and the..
和..
planetarium
天文馆
Do you want to go abroad?
你想出国吗？
um...
嗯…
yeah
是啊
I'd like to go to Majorca
我想去马略卡
and take a couple of weeks out there for everything
花上几周 那里的一切
relax myself
放松自己
I think I might like to, sort of, go out of this country
我想我可能喜欢，那种， 离开这个国家
probably just for a holiday
也许只是一个假日
first... somewhere... anywhere...
首先。在某处…在任何地方…
and then sort of..
然后点..
think about
想一想
settling down somewhere else
其他地方安定下来
I mean, I could have got a job
我的意思是，我可以得到一份工作
in..
在..
some foreign parts
国外的一些部分
working for some an auto.. packing firm
一些自动工作。包装公司
but when it came down to it I didn't want to move, I didn't want to leave
但当它下来我不 想要离开，我不想离开
so, I mean
所以，我的意思是
I've probably got a very narrow view
我已经得到了 非常狭隘的观点
of life because I don't really like traveling
生命因为我不 真的很喜欢旅行
Does that worry you that you have that narrow view? - worry me?
那你担心你 狭隘的观点？担心我吗？
you keep asking if things worry me, no
你一直问的事让我担心，没有
Does it concern you then?
它关心你吗？
yeah, that's a different word
是的，这是一个不同的词
no, not really it doesn't really concern me
不太感兴趣 这真的不关我的事
And what would you want for the future?
那你要的未来？
watching my kids growing up and when they're grown up
看着我的孩子们长大的时候 他们长大了
maybe seeing their children grow up as well
也许是看到他们的孩子 成长为好
Looking at some of the earlier films it would seem that you had a sad childhood.
在一些早期的电影 似乎你有一个悲伤的童年。
You didn't have a dad and you didn't have a lot of material things.
你没有你和爸爸 没有很多物质的东西。
no, I wouldn't really call that a sad life
不，我不会真的 打电话的那个悲惨的生活
it's a different life to somebody with everything or
这是一种不同的生活 一切或什么人
thinks they have everything but I mean
认为它们有 但我说的一切
it doesn't matter if you've got
如果你有没关系
everything, all of the material things in the world, I mean
所有的一切，所有的 在世界上的物质的东西，我的意思是
you're not going to be happy anyway because you'll still want the next thing
你不会快乐的生活 因为你仍然想下个东西
down the road
沿着这条路
At the end of their very special day in London
在结束他们的很 在伦敦的特别的一天
after their trip to the zoo and the party
他们去后 动物园和方
we took our children to an adventure play ground
我们把我们的孩子 冒险游乐场
where they could do just what they liked
在那里他们可以做的 只是他们喜欢的
Those from a children's home set about building a house.
那些从儿童之家 建立一个房子。
There's Nicholas.
那是尼古拉斯。
And Tony.
托尼。
Andrew.
安得烈。
And Bruce.
布鲁斯。
John.
约翰。
Suzie.
苏西。
Jackie and her friends.
杰基和她的朋友们。
Give me a child until he is seven...
给我一个孩子，直到他七岁…
and I will give you the man.
我会给你一个男人。
This has been a glimpse of Britain's future.
这是一眼 英国的未来。